All right.
好的
Allegedly we're on Twitch.
听说我们已经在 Twitch 上了
Can somebody, is somebody
有人能
anybody on there can check?
在那边看看吗？
Yeah.
好的
And if you're lucky
如果幸运的话
you even hear yourself.
你甚至能听到自己的声音
All right.
好的
I'm going to open up this stupid thing
我要打开这玩意儿
so I can answer people who are just like looking at stuff on their thing.
这样我就可以回复那些正在看东西的人了
Okay.
行
Great.
太棒了
All right.
行了
Uh, thanks everyone.
呃 谢谢各位
Please.
来吧
Somebody, oh, there's zero people on Twitch.
还有人吗 哦 Twitch 上一个人也没有
Awesome.
真好
Okay.
行
So, uh, Hello, everyone.
呃 大家好
In case you are super confused
如果你们感到很困惑
I am the real Adam.
我是真正的亚当
Everything you heard last week was a lie.
上周你们听到的都是假的
Let's see.
我们来看看
Any questions from last week about the course?
对上周的课程有什么问题吗？
No?
没有？
Everyone feel like they're ARM masters?
大家都觉得自己是 ARM 专家了吗？
Expert ARM people?
ARM 专家吗？
No?
没有？
Not yet?
还没呢？
Do you want to be?
你们想成为专家吗？
So far, based on what you've done
基于你们目前的经历
what's the big difference between ARM and x86-64?
ARM 和 x86-64 有什么主要区别？
Or ARM64, because there are several versions of ARM.
或者 ARM64 因为 ARM 有多个版本
Loading registers suck.
加载寄存器真头疼
What was it? Say it again.
什么？再说一遍
Loading registers suck.
加载寄存器真头疼
What do you mean?
什么意思？
You don't like loading registers?
你不喜欢加载寄存器？
loading the same register multiple times
重复加载同一个寄存器
Ah, you don't like loading the same register multiple times.
啊 你不喜欢重复加载同一个寄存器
Interesting.
挺有意思的
Why? is that a problem?
为什么这是个问题？
Oh, with the big numbers and stuff?
哦 是因为处理大数之类的问题吗？
Big numbers, yeah.
大数 对
Big numbers are a big problem, right?
大数确实是个大问题 对吧？
And I know Rob talked about that, right?
我记得 Rob 也提过这个问题 对吧？
You only have 32 bits for a single instruction
每个指令只有 32 位
which fundamentally limits what...
这从根本上限制了你...
literals you can put in there.
能放进去的立即数
It always helps to think of, for me
个人觉得 这样想会好一点
like how would I design this if I was designing like the ARM compiler,
比如 如果我要设计 ARM 编译器 我会怎么设计
right?
对吧？
So you have 32 bits
所以你有 32 位
you need to like
你需要考虑
you have to deal with these limitations.
你得应对这些限制
Okay, so any other ARM comments, questions?
好的 关于 ARM 还有其他意见或问题吗？
Yes.
你说
ooh, say it again
再说一下
Yeah, so it gets tricky.
是的 这问题确实复杂
I mean, I'll be honest
实话说
I'm not like a...
我不是个...
Super ARM expert.
ARM 专家
I guess the big confession is
坦白讲
I didn't actually have to read any ARM when I was doing XNU analysis
在分析 XNU 时，我其实不需要阅读任何 ARM 代码
because it's actually way easier.
因为实际更容易
I had an x86 machine
我有一台 x86 机器
and at the time you could run the same operating system versions on both
你可以在两台机器上，运行相同版本的系统
and it was way easier to debug that.
这样调试起来容易得多
Plus, as we'll see as we go into things
随着我们深入探讨
it's way easier to read source code and the decompilation code
阅读源代码以及反编译代码更容易
rather than having to dig into the binary code
相较于研究二进制代码
but sometimes I would have to.
但有时候我不得不这么做
But, yeah, so if I remember correctly
不过 如果我没记错的话
the floating point registers on ARM are 128 bits
ARM 的浮点寄存器是 128 位
so they for sure have this problem.
所以它们肯定会有这个问题
I think the other thing probably to think about is, like, a lot of,
我觉得还需要考虑的是 很多情况下
you know, what you're doing is
你是
writing assembly code from the perspective of
你写汇编代码的角度是
you're doing assembly code  because
你写它是因为
there's shellcoding and ROP and all that stuff, right?
要写shellcode还有 ROP 之类的 对吧？
When you're doing exploitation
在进行利用时
you often can control instructions
你通常能控制指令
and do those kinds of things.
做这类的事情
But if you are writing an ELF file
但如果你在编写 ELF 文件
you don't need to load immediates from instructions.
你就不需要从指令中加载立即数
You can always load them from memory.
你总是可以从内存中加载
You have to probably then deal with...
你可能需要处理...
Compilers would have to deal with the performance trade-offs.
编译器需要处理性能权衡
So any big literal that they want to shove into a floating point register
所以任何要放到浮点寄存器的大常量
maybe goes into the...
可能会放入...
goes into BSS or something that they can then read from there
放入 BSS 或其他可以读取的地方
and shove it into the register that way through memory.
然后通过内存将其载入寄存器
Yeah, exactly.
没错
But it's probably faster to use the immediates
使用立即数可能更快
but then you have to worry about, you know
但你得考虑
compilers always have to deal with
编译器总是需要处理
which is exactly what you see, right?
正如你看到的
Your instructions get, the size of your code gets larger
你代码的大小会增加
when you have to do these things.
当你需要做这些弯弯绕绕的时候
Like if loading an immediate takes five instructions
比如用5条指令实现一个加载立即数
and you want to load a hundred of them
而你想要加载一百个
your code is getting this 5x increase.
你的代码会增加 5 倍
So that actually may be slower
所以这可能会变慢
because of caching and all this other stuff that has to happen
因为缓存和其他操作的影响
and you don't get the benefits of like,
你无法获得
especially like in a tight optimization loop
比如在一个高优化的循环中的好处
you may not like the...
你可能
Values and other things may not fit into L1 cache or the instruction cache
值和其他数据可能无法完整放入 L1 或指令缓存
because it's getting flushed because the instructions are so large.
导致缓存频繁命中失败然后刷新
This is why when building compilers
这就是为什么在构建编译器时
it's very much an art rather than a science
这更像是一门艺术
because depending on one person's workload
因为这取决于每个人的工作量
it may be faster to do it one way
某种方法可能更快
whereas another workload may be faster to do it a third way.
而另一种情况可能用第三种方法更快
Is there ambient music on the stream or just me hallucinating again?
直播里有背景音乐吗 还是我又幻听了？
i don't know i can't i have no way of testing that
我不知道 没法测试
so hopefully it's a good hallucination that's what you're doing
希望这是个好的幻听 这就是你在做的
should clarify that's on twitch
澄清一下，这是在 Twitch 上的留言。
i'm not just hallucinating where that came from
不是我的幻觉
okay other things
好的 其他事情
i think the other thing that
我觉得另一件事是
oh i don't really want to bring the slides
我其实不太想用幻灯片
but uh another thing that um rob very graciously
不过 Rob非常慷慨
is he here I said he would be here today.
他来了吗？本来答应今天来的
So I was going to say what a great job he did
我本来想说他做得真不错
but since he's not here
但既然他没来
I won't say that.
我就不说了
But specifically, there was a discussion of why is ARM so weird?
我们讨论了为什么 ARM 这么特别？
So a lot of you have been learning and dealing with x86.
所以你们很多人都在学习和使用 x86
So do you feel that ARM is weird?
所以你们觉得 ARM 特别吗？
Why?
为什么呢？
Besides the one we already talked about at 64 versus 32.
除了我们讨论过的 64 位和 32 位的区别外
Yeah, there's no push or pop.
没错 没有 push 或 pop 操作
That's weird.
真奇怪
What other things are weird?
还有什么奇怪的地方？
Yeah,
嗯
but well, I mean
不过 我是说
when you're coding
编程的时候
does the length of the instructions have anything
汇编指令的长度
when you're writing assembly?
在编写汇编时有影响吗？
Maybe, maybe not,
可能有 也可能没有
but yeah, what other...
不过 还有什么其他……
Yeah, the stack has to be 16-bit aligned.
是的 栈必须 16 位对齐
That is so weird.
这太奇怪了
I don't fully understand why.
我不太明白为什么
There must be some optimizations they can do because of that.
他们肯定基于这个做了一些优化
But yeah, that's also weird.
但是 这也挺奇怪的
What other things?
还有什么？
Do you guys remember how the conditional flags are set?
你们还记得条件标志是怎么设置的吗？
Yeah, there's a – so on x86, right
对 在 x86 上 就是这样
every single add compare instruction
每条加法、比较指令
will change the conditional flag registers.
都会改变条件标志寄存器
On ARM, you have to –
在 ARM 上 你必须 –
if you want an add to change the conditional registers
如果你想让加法指令改变条件寄存器
you have to do the add S
你必须使用带 S 的加法指令，即ADDS
which probably stands for set flags or something.
这可能是指设置标志 或类似的操作
So every – Every addition, multiplication
所以 每次加法、乘法等操作
these operations have an S variant added to the end that updates the flags
这些末尾加S 的变体指令，会更新标志位
which I guess can be nice
我觉得这样挺好的
because if you know you're already doing this
因为如果你知道要做这些操作
you can update the flags
你就可以更新标志位
and maybe the processor has to do less work on every add instruction
这样处理器在每个加法指令上可能就少做些工作
when it doesn't have to update these flags.
在不需要更新标志位的时候
So it gives more power.
这样就提供了更多的灵活性
What other weird things?
还有什么其他奇怪的地方？
To me, that's weird
我觉得这很奇怪
because you're just used to these.
因为你已经习惯了这些
You don't even think about the flags.
你甚至都不用想这些标志
They just get set.
它们会自动设置
Any other weird things?
还有其他奇怪的地方吗？
Using the linking register.
使用链接寄存器
Yeah, super weird.
是的 真奇怪
Rather than pushing the stack also for pROPedure calls, right?
而不是在过程调用时也用栈 对吧？
So the fact that registers are always passed into
寄存器总是被传入
or parameters are always passed into the register is kind of weird.
参数总是传入到寄存器 这挺奇怪的
And also weird that like the same first argument
而且很奇怪 传递给函数的第一个参数
passed into the function is also the return thing
竟然也是返回值
which I don't know
这一点我不太懂
maybe there's some weird optimizations why that makes sense.
可能出于某些优化的考虑 所以才会这样设计
But is there anything you'd like about ARM?
你们对 ARM 有什么喜欢的点吗？
yeah cool 32-bit align. what else?
好，32位对齐，还有吗？
loading multiple registers at the same time
同时加载多个寄存器
Loading multiple registers with the STP and LDP
用 STP 和 LDP 指令加载多个寄存器
right pairs of registers
是的，寄存器对
disassembly is very easy because of this fact, right?
因为这个，反汇编都变简单了对吧？
You don't have this madness
你不会遇到这种疯狂的情况
where you have to guess about how long the instruction sizes are.
你不需要猜测指令的长度
And then when you're doing the problem of identifying functions in a binary
在处理二进制文件中的函数识别问题时
it makes it way easier
这会让事情简单很多
because you can just know exactly where the instructions are.
因为你清楚地知道指令的位置
Yeah.
对
Anything else?
还有其他问题吗？
Nobody likes the super, like
没有人喜欢
I feel like this should, like
我觉得这应该
speak to your computer science souls, that, like
会触动你们的计算机科学心灵
the registers are just 0 through 31
寄存器命名直接从 0 到 31
and they start at 0
并且从 0 开始
and there's no weird names that you have to remember
没有那些奇怪的名字需要记住
of, like, A, B, C, D,
像 先是A, B, C, D
but then RSI and all these other registers,
然后 RSI 等其他寄存器
RDI
and the shit that doesn't make sense.
还有那些让人看不懂的东西
Like, no, it's just, you know, X0 through X31
不 就是 X0 到 X31
and these are your registers.
这些就是寄存器
Does anybody else like that?
有人喜欢这样吗？
Yeah, I was going to say the calling convention is really nice.
对 我想说调用约定很好
Yeah, the calling convention being defined in the architecture,
我觉得架构中定义调用约定
I think, is important, right?
很重要 对吧？
Because if you've done x86
因为如果你用过 x86
you know that the calling convention is different on Linux versus Windows.
你会知道 Linux 和 Windows 的调用约定不同
And you can even in one project have different calling,
甚至在同一个项目中 也可以有不同的调用约定
C calling conventions,
C 调用约定
standard call, cdecl, all this stuff.
标准调用，cdecl调用 等等
And it just makes interoperability really difficult.
这使得互操作性变得非常困难
My guess is that's something that they learned from those architectures
我猜他们从中吸取了教训
of how bad it is when you have different things.
不同的调用约定有多么糟糕
Does anybody miss fights between Intel and AT&T syntax?
有人怀念 Intel 和 AT&T 语法之间的争斗吗？
Yeah, there's no difference.
没什么区别
It's just this is the way it is.
就是这样
You want to do it another way?
你想换个方式吗？
Just too bad.
太遗憾了
Any other good thoughts?
还有其他好主意吗？
The super long instructions?
超长的指令？
You mean like having like 10 arguments?
你是说有 10 个参数？
Yeah, that's like bonkers.
是的 那真够疯狂的
I hate that part.
我讨厌这部分
But it seems kind of ironic, right?
但这也挺讽刺的 对吧？
Because you think like RISC Reduced Instruction Set Computing should mean
因为你觉得精简指令集应该是意味着
that there's each thing does one simple thing and then it should be
每条指令只做一件简单的事
but then you can have really complex instructions.
但却能有非常复杂的指令
So why is it so weird?
所以它为什么这么奇怪呢？
That was kind of the point I wanted to discuss.
这正是我想讨论的重点
Because it's not x86, yes, I mean, that's correct.
因为这不是 x86 对 这是正确的
But you could make
但是你可以做出
has anybody done Yan85?
有人做过 Yan85 吗？
Yan85 is not, I guess it's weird in its own way.
Yan85 也有它自己独特的地方 挺奇怪的
Actually, it's probably more similar to ARM, but anyways.
其实它更像 ARM 不过算了
So, like, why is it weird?
那为什么它这么奇怪呢？
Ah, okay, familiarity.
啊 明白了 是因为熟悉
I would definitely buy that.
我完全赞同
That's cool.
挺好的
I think there's actually, like
我觉得其实有
a technical reason why this stuff is weird.
技术上的原因让这些显得奇怪
Like, why is there an add and an adds?
比如说 为什么有 add 和 adds？
Or why is there a load register, right?
或者为什么有加载寄存器 对吧？
LDR, you could do the prefix, postfix, and memory dereferences,
LDR 可以处理前缀、后缀 还有内存解引用
and register, like
还有寄存器
you could do like five different things in like one instruction.
你可以在一条指令中做五种不同的操作
This feels like ARM was made more to be created
感觉 ARM 更适合由机器生成
rather than written by people.
而不是由人来编写
Ah, interesting.
有趣
I haven't thought about that
我以前没想过
but that does make sense.
但确实有道理
I mean, if you think about it, right?
我是说 仔细想想 对吧？
Yeah, like assembly code should not be written by humans, just like
是的 汇编代码不应该由人类编写 就像……
I don't know
我不知道
has anybody done web stuff?
有人做过网页开发吗？
Do you like hand write HTML code all the time?
你喜欢一直手写 HTML 代码吗？
You can, but you can, you know
可以 但你可以
shunt that off to something else
交给其他工具处理
or you use an ORM wrapper that talks to the database
或者用 ORM 封装器与数据库通信
so you don't have to write SQL, right?
这样你就不用写 SQL 了 对吧？
This is kind of thinking out of the low level thing that you don't need.
这是不需要考虑底层细节的思维方式
Another thing is like, okay
还有
so there's no push and pop.
没有 push 和 pop 操作
Why is there no push and pop in ARM?
为什么 ARM 里没有 push 和 pop 操作？
you know you you
你知道的 你
you have the equivalent of a push and pop right
你有类似 push 和 pop 的操作
that auto increments the stack pointer
这会自动递增栈指针
that you don't have to use the stack
你不需要直接用栈
Yeah, so you can think like it's more abstract, I would say
是的 你可以认为 这更抽象
rather than push and pop that sets dedicated register.
而不是像 push 和 pop 用专用寄存器
You could technically use different registers to push and pop things, too.
你也可以使用不同的寄存器来执行 push 和 pop 操作
ah great food twitch already got you guys
啊 Twitch 已经解决了你们的问题
they're like 30 seconds behind this stream so
他们大概落后了这个直播 30 秒
even though i won't i don't know if i want to say names on stream
我不确定要不要在直播时提名字
but because this is well recorded
因为这会被录下来
but uh
但
yeah this person's hallucinating music
嗯 这个人幻听到音乐
but still was able to get there
但还能跟得上
it'd be a waste of four bytes right
浪费四个字节对吧
every instruction is four bytes so
每条指令都是四个字节 所以
if you had a push instruction that does one thing
如果你有一个只做一件事的push指令
That takes up, like, from your, like, if you think
这会占用 如果你这么想
if you think of, like
如果你想想
what are all the different instructions you can encode in four bytes
所有可以用四个字节编码的不同指令
Your limit, you can have two to the 32 technically
理论上 上限是 2 的 32 次方
but you fundamentally can't have that.
但实际上你不可能有那么多
So you can do things like with Yan85
所以你可以像 Yan85 那样处理
where you have the first byte, which is
其中第一个字节用来
defines which instruction it is, right?
定义这是哪条指令 对吧？
So, but fundamentally, if you go that route
所以 如果你选择这样做 从根本上说
you are wasting all the rest of the bytes
你会浪费掉
that don't specify that instruction
不用于指定指令的其他字节
because this push or this pop.
因为这些 push 或 pop 命令
So this is really, in my view
依我看 这正是
this is like the fundamental difference between x86 and ARM.
这是 x86 和 ARM 的根本区别
Because you don't want to have these special purpose instructions
因为你不希望有这些专用指令
like push or pop that are just for this one operation.
像push或pop这类只做某一操作的指令
Because you're wasting an entire possibility
因为你会浪费掉一个机会
that you could jam stuff in.
可以用来塞更多内容
It's the same reason why you have add and add s.
这也是为什么有 add 和 add s
Because you have an add instruction and everything else
已经有了add 和其他的指令
but there's probably an extra bit there.
但可能还有一比特可用
They're like, what are we going to do with this?
他们会想 这一比特怎么用？
Like, well, let's make it useful and expose it.
嗯 让我们把它用起来
Or like...
或者……
The other thing that's crazy to me is like
还有一件让我觉得不可思议的是
loading in constant values with left shifts a certain amount, right?
通过左移一定的位数加载常量值 对吧？
That's just like efficient usage of the 32 bits that you have.
这样就能充分利用 32 位
So this is like
所以这就像……
it's like almost like a bin packing problem or something, right?
几乎就像是一个装箱问题 对吧？
that the designers have to do of these RISC architectures.
这也是 RISC 架构设计师们需要考虑的
Um, so anyways, that's kind of
嗯 总之
I think that's why it's interesting
我觉得这就是为什么
to think of these things as like the technical decision
把这些问题看成技术决策很有趣
to be like, okay
就像是 好吧
we will have four byte instructions
我们有四字节指令
almost forces you to be efficient with the instructions that you have
这几乎迫使你更高效地使用现有的指令
and have each instruction be as flexible as the bits that remain allow it to be.
并且让每个指令尽可能灵活
So you'll just tack on all this weird junk to it.
所以你就会给它加一堆奇怪的玩意儿
Cool.
不错
Okay.
行
Any other questions or thoughts on that stuff?
关于这些内容还有其他问题或想法吗？
Okay, now, is the screen black?
行 现在屏幕是黑的吗？
I can't see what's going on.
我看不见发生了什么
Okay, perfect.
行 完美
Okay, so now it will be choose your own adventure.
行 现在选一下接下来的内容
So I'm kind of still figuring out
我还在尝试弄清楚
as you maybe saw last week
就像上周你们看到的
I didn't even really know what the name of this class was.
我甚至都不知道这门课叫什么
I only knew the AVR.
我只知道 AVR
Well, I did have it write on the syllabus, but...
不过 我确实把课程名称写在了教学大纲上 但是……
So the... Big thing that I'm trying to do is
所以 我努力做的……大事是
figuring out how in the world to get you all access to a XNU system
正在想办法让大家能够访问到一个 XNU 系统
so that you can hack on it and stuff.
以便你们可以在上面进行破解等操作
minimizing costs and getting everything to run so
尽量降低成本 让一切顺利运行
hopefully I'll have that in a week or two or so
希望一两周内能够搞定
so we're spending this time getting ready for ready for that
这段时间我们都在为此做准备
and doing learning arm stuff or sorry
同时也在学习 ARM 相关内容
yeah arms arm 64
是的 ARM64
so today
所以今天
and I think what I also want to do is make sure
我还想确保
that you guys are getting some discussion
大家能够进行一些讨论
and understanding of actual like applied vulnerability research
了解和实际应用中的漏洞研究
right finding stuff on real targets
也就是在真实系统中找漏洞
so I have basically two different topics today
今天我有两个主要话题
that we're gonna cover.
我们今天会讲到
One goal is ROP.
一个重点是 ROP
So we're gonna look at ARM
我们会研究 ARM
and do ROP ARM and study that.
并在 ARM 上进行 ROP 研究
And then I also have a discussion slash lecture on target selection.
另外 我还会讨论如何选择目标
So like how to go about even the first step
比如 如何开始第一步
before you wanna try to find vulnerabilities in a real system.
在你尝试发现真实系统中的漏洞之前
What system do you wanna find vulnerabilities in?
你想要在哪个系统中找漏洞？
So I will, I don't know how to let you decide
我不知道如何让你们决定
but I'll let you decide which one we wanna do first.
但你想让你们决定先说哪个
What was that?
什么？
I can't hear.
我听不见
Oh, coin toss.
哦 抛硬币
Oh, that's cool.
哦 挺不错的
Anybody else have another idea?
还有人有别的主意吗？
Yeah.
你说
That's the same idea.
那是一样的想法
They just slipped each other out.
他们只是没配合好
Okay.
好的
Which one do we want as which?
我们要哪个当哪个？
Heads will be ROP and tails will be target selection.
正面是 ROP 反面是目标选择
Siri, flip a coin.
Siri 抛个硬币
It's tails.
是反面
Oh, no, this one says it's tails
哦 不 这个说是反面
but this one says it's heads
但这个说是正面
so we have to do it again.
所以得再做一次
Okay, this is insane.
这太离谱了
Does anybody remember which one was which?
有人记得哪个是哪个？
Head ROP?
正面是ROP？
Head ROP, okay.
正面是ROP，好的
Flip a coin.
抛硬币
Heads, okay, so we're doing ROP first.
正面 好的 先讲ROP
All right, cool.
好的 太棒了
So, you will, okay
所以 你来 好的
so the next module is going to be ARM
所以下一个模块是 ARM
I should call it, ARM64 ROP, to be more specific.
我应该叫它 ARM64 ROP 这样更具体
Okay, the first assignment will be ARM ROP, or the next assignment, sorry
好的 第一个任务是 ARM ROP 或者说是下个任务 抱歉
because we already have one assignment.
因为我们已经有了一个任务
This will launch at 8 p.m. tonight.
今晚 8 点启动
I think that's kind of a decent cadence.
我觉得这个节奏还可以
It'll launch at 8 p.m.
8 点启动
and then do the next week.
然后是下一周
We'll probably have two-week assignments, just depending on how long
我们可能会有两周一次的任务 具体取决于任务的长度
and how difficult the things take.
以及任务的难度
For this in particular...
这个任务尤其如此
So it's a little bit tough
所以有点难
and it's gonna be something that hopefully will be easier going forward
但希望以后会简单一些
but you have to understand
但你得明白
that you are running right now in Pwn College on an x86-64 host
你当前在 Pwn 学院的 x86-64 主机上运行
but you will have an ARM binary that you need to pop.
但你需要运行一个 ARM 二进制文件
That is the goal.
这就是目标
So let's go in there.
那么让我们开始吧
Okay.
好的
So there should be some stuff in here about how to do this.
这里应该有一些关于如何操作的说明
It actually is even more of a pain
实际上 这更麻烦
because your favorite tools like object dump
因为你的常用工具 比如 objdump
you can't even use correctly because object dump will say
你甚至不能正确使用 因为 objdump 会报错
I don't understand this file format
不支持这种文件格式
because the one you have installed is the one with your architecture.
因为你安装的是和你架构匹配的版本
So you have to install other packages.
所以你需要安装其他包
I should have installed everything in there
我本应该把所有东西都装上
but like this is
但这次
I think the first time we've done on pwn.college
我觉得这是我们第一次在pwn学院
is like cross architecture stuff.
做跨架构的项目
So I just solve a lot of insane problems that I really am upset about
所以我解决了很多让我很头疼的问题
that I can talk to you about later.
这些问题我之后再和你细说
It also means that debugging
这也意味着调试时
and using GDB is a two-step process.
使用 GDB 要分两步进行
You can't just GDB an ARM binary
你不能直接用 GDB 调试 ARM 二进制文件
and expect GDB to somehow figure out magically what's going on.
期望 GDB 能神奇地搞清楚一切
So we'll go over that real quickly.
我们很快就会讲到这一点
So what we'll do is I'll start off with how to get started in this thing.
我先讲讲如何开始这个过程
And then we'll go to slides
然后进入幻灯片
talk about like how to even approach this
讨论如何入手这个问题
why it's different than x86.
为什么它与 x86 不同
You should all have already experienced using ROP on x86-64
你们都应该在 x86-64 上使用过 ROP
so that should be very familiar.
所以应该都很熟悉
The goal here is to then
这里的目标是
and really the goal of this course is to try to
这门课程的真正目标是
abstract your knowledge away
提炼你的知识
from just the one thing that you know, right?
把你已知的抽象出来
You know ROP on x86
你了解 x86 上的 ROP 对吧？
but what is ROP, right?
但 ROP 是什么呢？
What does that fundamental thing mean?
这个基本概念意味着什么？
How do differences in the architecture take
不同的架构如何影响
how differently you approach exploiting this stuff.
你利用这些漏洞的方法？
And then we'll go back.
然后我们再回到这个问题
I also found a CTF challenge.
我还找到了一个 CTF 挑战
I was thinking it'd be fun to hack together for a while
我觉得我们可以花点时间一起来破解这个二进制文件
and break this binary.
这会很有趣
It's supposed to be a very simple ARM binary that we can go to
这是一个简单的 ARM 二进制文件 我们可以用来练习
because I don't want to spoil your fun
我不想破坏你的乐趣
by showing you how to do any of this stuff
我不想展示这些
because I expect you to do that on your own.
我希望你自己搞定
All right.
好的
And then let's see.
我们来看看
Oh, this is a super giant class that I've like long in time-wise
哦 这是一门超长的课程
that I've never taught this long before.
我从没上过这么长时间的课
So I have absolutely no idea how this is going to go.
所以我完全不知道会怎么样
We started at 4.30.
我们从 4 点半开始
Let's do set a timer for a half hour.
我们设个半小时的计时器吧
That way we can take like a bio break in a half hour.
这样半小时后我们就可以休息一下
Okay.
行
Cool.
行 酷
Okay.
明白了
So this is hidden.
这个是隐藏的
You can't see this
你看不到这个
so don't bother doing it.
所以别浪费时间
Also, it turns out it's a really bad idea when you tell like 20, 30
另外 让 二三十个学生同时开始挑战
100 students to all start a challenge at the same time.
或者 100 个学生一起开始，真是个坏主意
The dojo can't quite handle that yet.
道场还应付不来
We're working on it.
我们正在努力解决
Actually, technically we should have a fix by Friday
事实上 我听说最晚周五就能修复这个问题
is what I've been told.
这是我被告知的
Practice mode doesn't work on this.
练习模式在这儿不行
I'm not sure exactly why.
我不太清楚为什么
It's something that I'm going to complain to Connor about to fix.
我会找康纳抱怨 让他修
I can get into all the nitty gritty gory details, but okay.
我可以讲得更详细 不过就算了
Do you all care about, like
你们在乎这些问题吗？
I feel like you guys are experienced enough.
我觉得你们经验足够了
I can use SSH and not have to worry about this stupid GUIs and stuff.
我可以直接用 SSH 不用管这些麻烦的界面
Okay, cool.
好的 挺好的
Cool.
好的
So I started my challenge.
我开始了挑战
Wow, okay.
哇 行
Okay, similar thing, everything's in challenge.
好的 一切都包含在挑战中
The binary will be in level whatever whatever, level dash one dash zero.
二进制文件在level-xx-xx 比如 level-1-0
The zeros have a little walkthrough, a little teaching
后面是0的会有一些引导和教程
and the ones are slightly different.
是1的稍微有所不同
This run, can you all read that, you in the back?
这次运行 大家都能看到吗 后面的也能看到？
Read screen?
看看屏幕
Good, okay.
好的 行
Yeah, this just executes the emulator and executes the challenge.
是的 这会运行模拟器并执行挑战
So there shouldn't be anything there.
所以那里不会有别的什么了
I think I did this all correctly by clearing the environment
这样做应该能清空环境变量
and all this stuff
以及相关内容
because there's weird QEMU variables
因为有一些奇怪的 QEMU 变量
you can set to get debugging as we'll show you.
你可以设置，以用于调试。 之后会展示
So hopefully that's not there
所以希望那里没有这些变量
but if you find a bypass
但如果你发现了绕过的方法
please let me know right away.
请马上告诉我
The point is to have fun and do this stuff.
重点是享受过程并完成这些任务
Okay, so if we just run it
好的 如果我们直接运行
this should be very
这应该非常……
I think this is very similar to the x86-64 ROP challenges.
我觉得这和 x86-64 的 ROP 挑战很像
I will probably add...
我打算再加几个...
I think there's like four or five other challenges I will add
我可能再加四个或者五个挑战
that will be pretty cool and fun to show you some differences.
来展示一下不同之处，那会很有趣
One with like a statically linked binary with like thousands of gadgets
一个静态链接的二进制文件里有成千上万的gadget
that you have to figure out how to tweak your way through.
你得想方设法排列好它们
And then one with a different compiler
还有一个用了不同编译器的
because we'll talk about that in a second.
稍后我们会讨论这个
So anyways, there's a win function.
总之 这里有一个win函数
The win function address is here.
win 函数的地址就在这里
You need to call that function.
你需要调用这个函数
We need to overflow the saved return address.
我们需要覆盖保存的返回地址
So again, this is and we'll look at this in a second
所以 我们一会儿再详细讲
but this is on The calling convention, right?
这涉及调用约定 对吧？
So we have a BL call
所以我们有一个 BL 调用
which go which redirects control flow usually to the start of a function
它通常将控制流重定向到函数的开头
and will store the return address in the register X30
并把返回地址存储在寄存器 X30 中
and Then when the program wants to when the function is done
然后当函数执行完毕后
it calls a ret to return back to register X 30
它调用 ret 返回到寄存器 X 30
Okay So here, 139 bytes
好的 这里有 139 个字节
means you need at least 147, yada, yada, yada.
意味着你需要至少 147 个字节 等等
I'm sure you all read this very in-depth every single time
我相信你们每次都读得很仔细
and don't just do something like this.
不要随便这么做
Okay, great.
好的 很好
And it does the printing of the ROP gadgets.
它会打印出 ROP gadget
It's actually, as we'll talk about in a second
实际上 我们待会儿会讨论
this is actually kind of not super helpful.
这实际上不是特别有帮助
This kind of can be helpful for your first one
这种对于你第一次来说可能会有帮助
but as you will find
不过你会发现
your ROP payloads are very different on ARM rather than x86.
在 ARM 上 你的 ROP 代码与 x86 有很大区别
So I crashed it, got a segmentation fault.
于是我把它搞崩溃了 出现了一个段错误
Awesome.
太棒了
If I pop this
如果我能pop它
I should get the flag and it should be good.
我应该能拿到flag 应该没问题
Some tools.
一些工具
I have to go copy this
我得复制这个
because I do not recall this exact thing.
因为我记不清这个具体的了
All right.
好的
objdump -d for disassemble.
用objdump反汇编
And then I can look at this whole big guy.
然后我能看看整个内容
And then I can get into the habit of reading ARM code
然后我可以开始熟悉读 ARM 代码
which is part of what you're learning here.
这是你们在这里要学的
So setting up the stack frame, subtracting B0 from the stack frame,
设置栈帧 减去 B0
storing X29 and X30.
存储 X29 和 X30
Why is it doing this store?
为什么要存储？
And the link register.
还有链接寄存器
So again, another x86 difference, right?
这是 x86 的另一个区别 对吧？
In what usually takes two or three instructions for x86-64 to do.
通常 x86-64 需要两到三条指令
This does it in one.
这里用一条指令就完成了
Does that really matter for performance?
这对性能真的有影响吗？
Yeah, maybe.
嗯 也许吧
I mean, it really depends.
这得看具体情况
You have to get down into lower, like, micro-architectural things.
你得深入到微架构层面
If you learned MIPS and the MIPS pipeline, you would see, like, well, yes
如果你学过 MIPS 和它的流水线 就会明白确实如此
if you can do in one instruction what it takes three instructions to do
如果一条指令能完成三条指令的工作
that one instruction will definitely be faster.
那这条指令肯定会更快
Because with three instructions
因为三条指令
you have to have three things in the pipeline
流水线中要处理三件事情
and worry if they invalidate things
还得担心它们会使某些东西失效
and things can just go slower that way.
这样就会更慢
The unfortunate truth is on modern hardware, all of this stuff
不幸的是 在现代硬件上，这些东西
probably even on ARM
甚至在 ARM 上也一样
I actually don't know for a fact
我也不确定
but I'm positive they probably do something like this
但我相信他们也会这样做
gets compiled down into micro-code that gets executed.
会被编译成微代码来执行
So even what is three instructions or one instruction on x86-64
所以 即使是 x86-64 上的三指令或一指令
may get compiled down to like 10 instructions
也可能被编译成 10 条指令
or 10 micro instructions that are doing stuff.
或者是 10 条微指令
And that actually enables the CPU to do things out of order and crazy things
这使得 CPU 能够乱序执行和其它疯狂的事
as long as what you see in the caches
只要缓存中的内容
is all consistent based on the architecture.
与架构保持一致
So this is why it's super hard to say like,
所以很难说
look, one instruction versus three instructions. This is clearly better.
一条指令比三条指令更好
It's like, that's not really the world we live in.
现实不是这样
And so you just have to run experiments
所以你只能通过实验来验证
and then what you measured is true for that CPU
然后你的测量结果只适用于那款 CPU
which may not abstract or be applied.
这些结果可能无法应用于其他地方
Okay.
好的
Cool.
酷
Okay.
好的
So yeah, storing those things.
所以 把这些东西存起来
Cool.
酷
Okay.
行
So now we can look at stuff.
现在我们可以看看这些东西
I guess I did want to show you the workspace just because...
我想展示一下工作区 因为……
Wait, what?
等一下 什么？
Wait, how am I seeing this?
等等 我怎么能看到这个？
Are you guys seeing this?
你们看到这个了吗？
Did I get logged out?
我是不是登出了？
Yeah, whatever.
嗯 随便啦
Okay.
行
The other thing that's really annoying is
还有件烦人的事
there's only like two decompilers installed.
这里只装了两个反编译器
Good old IDA.
还是那个 IDA
Anybody use IDA?
有人用 IDA 吗？
Yeah.
有
There's a problem with IDA.
IDA 有个问题
Anybody know what it is before I click ok
有人知道是什么问题吗 在我点ok之前
It doesn't have any arm.
它不支持 ARM
The free version of IDA is only x86 and x86 64.
IDA 的免费版只支持 x86 和 x86-64
So that sucks.
这真是太糟糕了
I don't know what to tell you, but...
我也不知该怎么说了 但是……
So anyways, it will not work on Pwn College on these challenges.
总之 它在 Pwn College 上的这些挑战行不通
You can, actually for a lot of these you can use objdump.
其实这里很多情况，你都可以用 objdump
Apparently Ghidra works.
看来 Ghidra 可以用
angr management does not it hasn't been Nixified.
angr管理还没有被 Nix 化
I definitely agree.
我完全同意
see, build NIX.
看，build Nix
Anyways, that's the big problem is they needed to get the ability to,
总之 最大的问题就是他们需要获得这样的能力来...
Like for this
比如这个
I needed special libraries installed
我需要安装特定的库
and special like the QEMU emulator and all that stuff.
比如 QEMU 模拟器等工具
And so rather than going in and installing it
所以与其进入环境逐一安装它们
so that it's on every single Pwn College challenge that ever gets launched
让每个Pwn College 的挑战无论何时启动都能配备
we now have the ability to define your own Docker container
我们现在可以定义自己的 Docker 容器
that I can say these challenges need this Docker container.
我可以指定这些挑战需要这个 Docker 容器
But you also want things like this interface and everything.
但你还想要这样的界面和其他功能
And you don't want to have to...
你肯定不想...
Oh, man, Connor's going to if he hears this
康纳要是听见了...  他一定会发飙
don't in any way tell him
千万别告诉他
because this is me regurgitating all the good stuff
因为我现在在讲好的部分
because this next thing is terrible.
接下来可就糟了
But it has a lot of great benefits
但它有很多优点
where you can still get this X server
你还是可以使用这个 X 服务器
and all this stuff in here
还有这里的所有内容
which I didn't have to install in my container.
这些都不用安装在我的容器中
My container is literally just ubuntu 2404 base
我的容器就是基于ubuntu 2404
installed the things I need
装了我需要的东西
and you can do that here.
你也可以在这里这样设置
Anyways, so eventually we'll get those other tools ready to go.
不管怎样 我们最终会把这些其他工具准备好
New project.
新项目
Oh, God, I hate this stuff.
哦 天哪 我真讨厌这些
project
项目
sorry i'm just trying to be a good person to show you how to use this
我只是想做个好人，展示一下怎么用这个
open import yep
打开 导入？ 是的
This is why it's so difficult.
这就是为什么这么难
Don't learn anything new.
不要学新东西
Just learn something and just get used to that forever.
学一点东西 然后一直用下去
Use it for the rest of your life and never learn anything new.
用一辈子 别学新东西
That's my advice.
这是我的建议
Oh, I didn't.
哦 我没...
It's not been analyzed.
还没分析过
Would you like to...
你想...？
No, I would just like to look at the binary.
不 我想看0101
Of course I want you to analyze it.
我当然想让你分析一下
Oh, come on.
拜托了
Hey, okay.
嘿 行
There we are.
好了
Wait, why does this font look weird?
等等 这字体怎么怪怪的？
Is this how it always looks?
它一直都是这样吗？
Is it really?
真的吗？
Oh, God.
哦 天啊
I'm so sorry.
真对不起
Some people get used to this
有些人习惯了
and I don't understand why
我也不明白为什么
but I respect people's ability to get...
但我尊重大家能习惯这点
Okay.
好吧
I mean, I do kind of like them side by side
我觉得这样并排显示也挺好的
but I don't know.
但我也说不准
You just get so used to IDA.
你们对 IDA 已经非常习惯了
Anyways, so there you go.
就这样了
You have the disassembly on the right, the assembly on the left.
右边是反汇编 左边是汇编
No, I guess we can use angr management.
我们可以试试angr
Is Zion, no, Zion's not here
齐昂不在这里
but let's see.
我们来看看
There should be a decompiler on the command line here.
命令行里应该有个反编译器
We'll just do all the functions.
我们来反编译所有函数
There's no way this is going to work.
这肯定不行
What do you think?
你觉得呢？
Should we put bets? Is it going to work?
打个赌吗？赌一下这能行吗？
Errors.
出错了
Always great to see.
看到这总是挺好的
This is when you kill it
这就该结束了
because you realize this was a terrible idea and you go
因为你意识到这是个坏主意 然后你这么做
Adam burning up the, hey, that actually worked.
亚当耗 嘿 居然成功了
Okay, cool.
行 真酷
So anyways, angr management doesn't work
总之 angr management图形界面不起作用
but angr is installed and you can get some kind of, you know
但angr已经安装了 你可以用来 你知道的
everyone knows C looks exactly like this.
大家都知道 C 就是这样写的
And this is valid C.
这是有效的 C 代码
But you can, let's see
但你可以 我们来看看
can you even see the buffer here?
你在这里能看到缓冲区吗？
So there should be a read.
所以应该有个读取操作
I'm just looking for a read.
我就是在找读取操作
Yeah, read into V1.
对 读取到 V1 中
V1 is the address of V4.
V1 是 V4 的地址
And V4 must be on the stack.
V4 应该在栈上
And V4, BP minus hex 93.
V4 的地址是 BP 减 0x93
So we actually do roughly know
所以我们对它大致有了解
like this actually gives us enough information about
这些信息已经足够了
where this is on the stack in relation
它在栈上的具体位置
so we should be able to pop this.
所以我们应该可以pop它
Let's double check that
我们再确认一下
that I can't do in my head conversions between binary and hex yet.
我还不能在脑子里快速转换二进制和十六进制
And then what did the challenge say?
那么挑战中怎么说的？
Did it say that it was 197?
它说的是 197 吗？
Look at that.
来看看这个
Hey, angr management got something right.
嘿 angr management这次居然做对了
Don't count on it though.
不过别指望它
Okay.
好的
Okay, so clear how to use it or start it.
好的 知道如何启动它了
Okay, wait, I guess let me show you one more way.
好的 等一下 我再给你演示一种方法
Just in case nobody's ever showed this to you.
万一之前没人给你演示过
So I'm using SCP secure copy uses SSH.
所以我用 SCP（安全复制） 它用 SSH
I'm going to SCP challenge.
我要用 SCP 传输挑战文件
And I press tab
然后我按 Tab 键
which always takes a little, there we go, level.
这通常需要一点时间 好了 这就搞定了
So copy this file to here.
所以把文件复制到这里来
What?
什么？
Why didn't that work?
为什么没成功呢？
Okay, anybody know the other trick?
好的 有谁知道其他的小技巧吗？
If you have SSH access, my friends
如果你有 SSH 访问权限 朋友们
you can always get a file.
你随时可以获取文件
This is a poor man's transferring of files.
这是一种土办法来传输文件
So what you're doing
所以你做的就是
if you've never done this or used this before
如果你之前没做过或没用过这个
you SSH and
使用 SSH 连接时
the last argument can be a command that you execute on the SSH connection.
最后一个参数可以是你想在这个 SSH 连接上执行的命令
So you SSH catting out the file
因此 你可以通过 SSH 使用 cat 命令输出文件
which will dump this to standard input of your terminal here.
这会将文件内容输出到终端的标准输入
And then you can just redirect that to here.
然后你可以将这些内容重定向到这里
And I've definitely done this.
我做过这个
You can also do this the other way.
你也可以反过来操作
You can cat a file
你可以用 cat 输出文件
pipe it to SSH
然后通过管道传递给 SSH
and then your command is cat dash
然后你的命令是 cat -
and then redirect that to a file.
然后将其重定向到一个文件
See, I'm working around, like
看 我在绕过这个问题
why did SCP not work?
为什么 SCP 不行？
I have no idea.
我也不知道
Do I want to debug it?
我想要调试一下吗？
Absolutely not.
绝对不想
Figure out a way to make it work.
想办法让它能用
It works.
搞定了
And if I really wanted to make sure
如果我真想确保的话
I would try to, like
我会尝试
MD5 both files to make sure they're exactly the same.
对比两个文件的 MD5 确保它们完全一致
I'm actually pretty confident.
我其实挺有把握的
So the other thing you can do is open
另外 你也可以打开
use SCP or this SSH method
使用 SCP 或 这个SSH 方法
and disassemble your buddy right here.
在这里反汇编
So much faster.
快多了
Yay, so there's main.
耶 main在这
Welcome, challenge.
欢迎挑战
I can look at challenge.
我可以查看这个挑战
V9, I bet that's our buffer.
V9 我猜应该是我们的缓冲区
Let's look at the read.
我们看看这个read
Buff equals V9.
buf 来自 V9
Read into buff.
数据读入缓冲区
And base pointer minus 98 hex.
基址指针减 98（十六进制）
Wasn't that exactly what we looked at before?
不就是我们之前看的吗？
No. 93 hex.
不 是 93（十六进制）
Fuck, it's because of stupid reasons that I don't understand.
靠 是因为我搞不懂的某些蠢原因
But they do them.
但他们就是这么做的
Oh, no, wait.
哦 不 等等
Yeah.
嗯
Anyways, I don't know why it does that, but look at the binary.
不管怎样 虽然我不清楚为什么 但看看这个二进制
That's my tip for all this stuff in these offsets
这是我对于这些偏移量内容的建议
because binaries don't lie.
因为二进制代码不会撒谎
Okay.
好的
Any questions about how to access the stuff?
怎么访问这些内容 有什么问题吗？
Oh, debugging.
哦 调试一下
Okay, great.
好的 太棒了
Nope, that's not what I want.
不 这不是我要的
Okay.
好的
So the other thing is...
还有就是……
Ah, why is this not installed?
啊 为什么这个没装上？
Screen?
I actually prefer screen.
我更喜欢screen
Anyways, this is a problem I could fix
不过 这个问题我可以解决
but I won't.
但我现在不解决
I mean, I will fix it later, but not now.
我意思是 我会稍后再解决
Okay.
好的
You need to, so first thing to do
你需要做的是 首先
so if you didn't, you know
如果你没这样做 你知道的
this is a grad class
这是研究生课程
so I kind of expect you all to poke around at stuff
我期望你们自己去探索这些东西
and not need to be handheld through all this stuff
而不是需要我手把手地教
but I want to show you how to think about approaching these things.
但我想给你们展示怎样思考如何解决这些问题
So we know what the challenges run
我们知道挑战题执行了什么
because we can see that it's running QEMU and then the challenge.
因为我们可以看到它正在运行 QEMU 然后是具体的挑战
So if we ever wanted to
所以如果我们想做的话
and if Rob was here
如果 Rob 在这里
he would tell us to pass dash h
他会说用 -h 参数
and read the man page for QEMU
并查看 QEMU 的帮助文档
or read the help documentation for QEMU.
或者查阅 QEMU 的帮助文档
And there's a ton of arguments in here.
这里有很多参数选项
The one that you can check out
你可以查看这一个
the one we care about right now, is debug.
我们现在关注的是调试
So just like, has anybody done debugging,
有人用过调试参数吗
like using QEMU system to debug a kernel?
用 QEMU 调试过内核吗？
I think you've implicitly done it in Pwn College without knowing it.
我认为你们在 Pwn College 时已经不知不觉地做过
If you've done the kernel modules
如果你完成了内核模块的练习
like VM debug actually creates QEMU
vm debug会创建 QEMU
and sets up a GDB server there to wait for your connection
并在那儿设置一个 GDB 服务器等待连接
and then you connect on another GDB instance.
然后你通过另一个 GDB 实例连接
Similar thing here, this is all built in.
这里也是类似的 这些功能都是内置的
So g 1234,
-g 1234
it's dash G, and then the port number,then the port number
-g 后面加上端口号
okay
好的
and then the binary challenge
接下来是二进制文件 challeng
and I would also recommend
我建议
it's a good for what we're trying to do
对我们做的很有益处
is a good idea to be used to things not working that should
习惯意料外的问题 是个好主意
so this for instance when I was doing vulnerability analysis on XNU
例如 我在对 XNU 进行漏洞分析时
I would There's a whole setup you can go through to load, to get
我需要经历一整套加载过程才能获取
I think it's KDB kernel debug on the kernel.
我记得是 KDB 内核调试
You can have it trigger a breakpoint
你可以让它触发一个断点
which then waits for a port just like this.
然后它就会像这样等待一个端口
It's actually a similar service and connect to it.
实际上是一个类似的服务 可以连接到它
You can set breakpoints amazingly.
你可以非常方便地设置断点
Then you break on that
然后你在那儿设置断点
and you try to single step.
然后尝试单步执行
It just doesn't work.
但就是不行
You can inspect memory and look at things.
你可以检查内存和其他内容
It just doesn't work.
但就是不行
I have absolutely no idea why.
我完全不清楚为什么
Do you think I want to spend weeks figuring out why I can't do this?
你觉得我想花几周时间弄清楚为什么做不到这一点吗？
No.
不
You figure out other ways around it to debug what you want to debug
你可以找到其他方法来调试你想要的内容
and just set breakpoints and look at things and then continue worked.
然后设置断点 查看状态 再继续运行
So that was fine.
这样就行
You can just set multiple breakpoints.
你可以设置多个断点
You have to be very flexible in what your target allows you to do.
你得灵活应对目标允许你做的事情
Okay, so why isn't this doing anything?
好的 那为什么它不工作呢？
Yeah, it's waiting for something to connect to the port, right?
是的 它在等东西连到端口 对吧？
You want to debug it
你想调试它
but it ran concurrently.
但它是在并发运行的
You want it to wait for you to connect to it to actually start debugging.
你希望它等你连接后再开始调试
So we need gdb-multiarch.
所以我们需要 gdb-multiarch
You will make that mistake of doing GDB
你可能会误用 GDB
and putting in the thing
然后加载程序
and there'll be slightly subtle errors.
结果会出现一些细微的错误
You'll connect to this thing
你会连接到程序
and it says stuff about XML
然后会显示一些关于 XML 的信息
which sounds like bonkers insane
这些信息听起来有点离谱
but you just have to realize you did not use the right GDB
但你得明白 问题是你没有使用正确的 GDB
because this stuff does work.
功能是可以工作的
So gdb-multiarch
所以 GDB 多架构
I'm setting that up here.
我正在这里设置
No debugging symbols.
没有调试符号
I don't have gef installed here.
我没有在这里安装 gef
And there is like a weird thing with gef to talk to a remote target.
而且 用 gef 跟远程目标通信时有点问题
I don't actually know if it works well or not.
我也不知道它能不能正常工作
I don't know, but...
我不知道 但是……
What you want is target remote.
你要执行target remote
I do localhost 1234.
我连接到本地 1234 端口
This is actually pretty cool if you think about it.
想想看 这其实挺酷的
Like what we're doing is connecting to a GDB server through a port.
我们通过端口连接到 GDB 服务器
So this, you know
所以 你知道的
conceptually what this allows you to do
这样你就可以
is debug a remote machine from your local GDB
用本地的 GDB 调试远程机器
which is really cool.
这真是太酷了
I think it's really cool.
我觉得这也挺酷的
So you technically could be running that GDB on your local machine,
所以你可以在本地机器上运行 GDB
SSH into Pwn College doing port forwarding.
通过 SSH 连接到 Pwn College 并进行端口转发
or doing local port forwarding through the remote one
或者通过远程机器进行本地端口转发
and then connect your GDB to that remote instance
然后将 GDB 连接到远程实例
and actually be able to do everything on your local GDB.
并且可以在本地 GDB 上完成所有操作
The problem there is that connection can be slow
问题在于这种连接可能会很慢
and like when you debug things, right?
在你调试时
All the state of the CPU
CPU 的所有状态信息
and registers that your GDB needs
以及 GDB 需要的寄存器信息
gets sent back over UDP and that can be slow.
会通过 UDP 发送回来 可能会很慢
So if you can get on the same host you want to
所以 如果能连接到同一台主机上
but in case you need to do this to debug two things
但你需要调试两件事时
it's very useful.
这非常有用
All right, great.
好的 很棒
Okay, target available.
好的 目标已就绪
So I am here.
所以 我在这里了
Breakpoint, continue.
断点 继续
And the other thing you need to be careful of is those register names
另一个需要注意的是这些寄存器名称
because you're used to x86 register names.
因为你习惯了 x86 的寄存器名称
You will type in RIP.
你会输入 RIP
You will type in all kinds of stuff that doesn't work.
你会输入各种不起作用的东西
EBP, you will get used to it
比如EBP。你会习惯的
Everything will be fine.
一切都会好起来的
Okay.
好的
And then here we can do everything we want.
在这里 我们可以做想做的事
We normally do in GDB, right?
做我们通常在 GDB 里做的
We can dump the stack, look at all kinds of stuff.
我们可以输出栈 查看各种信息
even though we're running the program inside of an emulator.
虽然我们在模拟器里运行程序
So it's emulating
它实际上是在模拟
like QEMU is emulating all those ARM instructions
QEMU 模拟所有的 ARM 指令
and figuring out all the stuff
处理各种事情
and then translating system calls and everything for you
还帮你翻译系统调用等
so you don't have to think about it.
这样你就不用操心了
Cool.
酷
So I can't digest Win.
所以我无法运行 Win
So why can't I just jump to Win if I knew how to find the address of Win?
如果我知道如何找到win的地址，我为什么不直接跳转过去
Good point, maybe.
好想法 可能吧
we are talking about in GDB or in ARM
是在说在gdb中，还是在arm里
in gdb
在gdb中
in gdb drops the privilege
在gdb中会降低特权级别
Yes, well, yes, but we, yeah,exactly,
嗯 是的
so we ran the QEMU as our user
我们用我们的用户运行的QEMU
QEMU should not be set uid root
QEMU 不应设SUID为 root
so it's not running as root
它不是以 root运行的。
so we can get QEMU to do anything
我们能让 QEMU 做任意事
and it will do it for us
并且它会为我们执行
but we can't get the flag
但我们拿不到 flag
right
对吧
so you have to run challenge run
所以你得运行 challenge run
this is why you should not be able to debug
这就是为什么你不能
the running instance that does get the flag
靠调试运行实例，拿到 flag
uh great okay
好的
thanks
谢谢
Some guy on the Twitch mentioned
有 Twitch 的观众提到
when you do the target remote
在远程调试时
you can drop the local host here.
可以省略 localhost
I like including it so you can completely remove that
我喜欢包括它 你可以完全删除它
and just do colon 1234.
然后直接写 :1234
That's the port you put into the dash G command.
这就是 -g 命令中的端口
I personally kind of like it
我个人挺喜欢这样做
because you are specifying exactly where to go
因为你明确指定了目标
and it reminds you that you can go other places
并且提醒你可以连接到其他地方
but do what you want to do.
但按你的喜好来做吧
Okay, any other questions here?
好的 还有其他问题吗？
I think this gets you up to speed and you can get going.
我觉得这能让您快速上手 可以开始了
Oh, great question.
哦 好问题
Does pwntools work with ARM payloads on here?
pwntools 支持生成这里的ARM payload吗？
The question is, I do not know.
问题是 我不清楚
I haven't tested that yet.
我还没有测试过
But you will tell me soon.
但你很快就会告诉我
I think so.
我想是这样
There's probably a packet that needs to install now that I think about it.
想来是需要安装一个包
Like for creating ARM payloads?
比如创建 ARM 载荷？
It does.
是的
Oh, it does.
哦 确实
Yeah, it already did.
对 它已经安装好了
Well, no, no, that was on the previous one.
不 那个是在之前的版本里
That's not this image
这不是这个镜像
so it may not work on this image.
所以它可能在这一版上不好用
I think pwntools installs pwntools.
我觉得 pwntools 会自己安装
I don't know.
我不知道
Yes.
是的
Yeah, it actually should be fine.
对 应该没问题
I don't know.
我不知道
I'm just thinking of if you ever need it
我只是在想 如果有一天你会用到
maybe you're doing some ROPk payload that does mprotect or something
可能你在做一些需要 mprotect 的 payload
and then you want to execute your own shellcode, basically
然后你可能需要执行自己的 shellcode
like making sure that pwn.assemble actually does work with ARM64.
比如确保 pwn.assemble 能支持 ARM64
It should, but...
应该可以 但是……
I haven't tested it.
我还没测试过
It's just what I'm saying.
我只是这么说的
So tell me if it breaks.
如果出问题了 告诉我
Yeah, but does it work here?
是的 但在这里能用吗？
Yeah, you need that special binutils thing
你得用那个特别的 binutils 工具
which I don't know how it does.
我也不清楚它是怎么弄得
Okay, any other questions here?
好的 还有其他问题吗？
Oh, great question.
哦 好问题
No, no, we're going to get there, Twitch user.
别急 Twitch 的朋友们 我们马上就会讲到
Maybe a stupid question, but isn't the return address in a register?
也许是个简单的问题 但返回地址不是在寄存器里吗？
How can we overflow?
我们怎么让它溢出呢？
Great question.
好问题
say it again
再说一遍
Yeah, let's look at the first instructions here.
我们来看看这里的前几条指令
So if we look at the challenge function here
所以 来看一下这里的 challenge 函数
the very first thing that happens is the stack pointer subtracts hex B0
首先 栈指针会从自身减去十六进制 B0
from the stack pointer
（从栈指针中）
puts it into the stack pointer
然后将结果存回栈指针
Also isn't this crazy?
这不是很疯狂吗？
Now you don't have implicit destination registers.
现在没有隐式的目标寄存器了
You actually are very explicit of where the thing goes.
你明确指出了数据的去向
I actually really like that.
我真的很喜欢这一点
It's cool.
这很酷
And then this one here, store pointer, STP, is going to...
接下来 存储指针指令（STP）将会...
Let's see.
我们来看看
I always have to remember how this is done.
我总是需要记住这是怎么操作的
I think this will store it at SP plus 160.
我认为这会把它存到 SP 加 160 的位置
So it'll take X29
所以会用 X29
put it at 160, and then put X30 at 160 plus 8.
放到 160 X30 放到 160 加 8
and store those registers in there?
然后把那些寄存器存进去？
Yes, okay, that actually
对 不错的 这
that also makes sense.
这也有道理
We can look at the documentation later
我们可以之后再看文档
and we'll do that in a second, but anyways, the point is
我们一会儿再做 但重点是
it's stored on the stack somewhere, right?
它会存到栈上的某个位置 对吧？
And why does it need to store the return address on the stack
为什么要将返回地址存到栈上呢？
if the return address is passed into a register?
返回地址不是传到寄存器中吗？
There's something right there in the register
寄存器里有东西
Something might be what?
那可能是什么呢？
Yeah,
嗯
but we just got called.
但我们刚被调用
We don't care about it.
我们不在乎
Somebody called us, but they put in that register X30 of where to go.
有人调用了我们 但把返回地址放到了寄存器 X30 中
So why do we need to store it onto the stack?
那为什么还要把它存到栈上？
What was it?
那是什么？
More specific.
具体点
Feels just like a word salad that you just said.
听起来就像你刚说的一堆词
Yeah, but when do you need to do that?
是啊 但什么时候需要这样做呢？
Does every function need to store the X30 onto the stack?
每个函数都需要把 X30 存到栈上吗？
Yeah, what's the leaf function?
嗯 什么是叶子函数？
And why is that important for this discussion?
为什么这对我们的讨论很重要？
So if there are less functions
如果函数更少的话
I think they don't need to call the register on the stack.
我认为它们不需要把寄存器存到栈上
Why?
为什么？
They're not going to get anything.
它们什么也得不到
Exactly.
没错
They're never going to get called
它们永远不会被调用
which means that it's totally fine.
这就没问题了
You're not calling any other functions.
你不会调用其他函数
So if your function ever needs to call another function
如果函数需要调用其他函数
you need to store X30 on the stack because it's a call.
你需要把 X30 存到栈上 因为这是一个调用
I mean, it seems silly calling it a caller-preserved register
它被称为调用者保存寄存器 听起来有点傻
because, of course
因为显然
it's the return address.
是返回地址
And when you call a BL
当你调用 BL
you need to come back.
你需要返回
And so...
所以……
But yeah, that's another one you think about why, right?
对 这也是个值得思考的问题 对吧？
Because I always like to think of like, oh, that's interesting.
因为我觉得 哇 这很有趣
It's different from x86.
它和 x86 不同
Why?
为什么？
I think it's because you can see
我认为这是因为你可以看到
that you can make leaf functions more efficient, right?
你可以让叶子函数更高效 对吧？
Rather than every single time you have a call instruction
而不是每次调用指令时
it shoves the address onto the stack.
都把地址压入栈中
When it leaf functions
处理叶子函数时
you don't need to do that.
你不需要这样做
So you're saving space there.
这样就省空间了
Very similar.
非常相似
Anybody remember the red zone in x86-64?
有人记得 x86-64 的红色区域吗？
Well, that's the question.
嗯 这就是问题
Yes, you're asking me.
是的 你在问我
Have you ever seen a function that writes past the stack pointer?
你见过函数超出栈指针写入的情况吗？
Right, so on, I believe it's like
对 接着 我认为是这样
I can't remember if it's like 128 bits
我不记得是不是 128 位
or something like that or bytes.
或者是字节
No, it can't be bits.
不 不可能是位
It must be bytes.
肯定是字节
But anyways, it's implicit stack space.
反正这是隐式的栈空间
So when your function is executing...
所以当函数执行时...
There is an implicit space that is saved that will not be if the
会有一个隐式空间被保存 除非...
I think it's like even if there's an interrupt or anything happens
我认为即使发生中断...
it's guaranteed that nobody will write to lower than I think
可以保证没有人会写入低于
it's 128 bytes of the stack.
128 字节的栈空间
ARM has the exact same thing.
ARM 也有同样的机制
And the reason is so that you have these optimizations,
这样做是为了实现这些优化
like a leaf function doesn't need to set up its own stack frame
例如 叶函数不需要为其自身设置栈帧
if it uses less than 128 bytes in its local function.
如果局部空间占用少于 128 字节
It doesn't need to do the decrementing stack.
不需要调整栈
And then in ARM it doesn't need to do the saving of the X30 register.
而在 ARM 架构中 不需要保存 X30 寄存器
So it's making these things more efficient
因此这些操作更加高效
and these special cases of these tail functions become way more efficient.
这些叶子函数的特殊情况也更高效
Cool.
真不错
What the hell were we talking about?
我们刚才在说什么来着？
Oh, yes, okay, yes.
哦 对 记得了
So there would probably then be
那么接下来可能会有
so if you have an overflow in a function that's a leaf function
如果你在一个叶函数中出现溢出
There's nothing to overwrite.
没什么可以覆盖的
There's no saved return address on the stack.
栈里没有保存的返回地址
That return address is in a register.
返回地址在寄存器里
You are just like SOL.
你就只能碰运气了
Well, of course, you could maybe have...
当然 你也可以……
Actually, that would be a fun challenge
那倒是个有趣的挑战
but you could probably
但你可能
depending on if the frame pointer needs to be saved or is saved
取决于帧指针是否需要或已被保存
then you could control the frame pointer.
你就能控制帧指针了
Otherwise, you can control whatever is stored in the function that calls you, right?
否则 你可以控制调用你的函数中的内容 对吧？
Cool.
不错
Okay.
好的
Yes, so this was all of the how can we overflow
对 这就是我们如何造成溢出的全部方法
which is exactly what we're talking about here.
这正是我们在说的
because this specific, this STP, exactly right here
因为这里这个特定的 STP 指令
stores the frame pointer and the link register onto the stack.
将帧指针和链接寄存器存入栈
And then if we go to the end of challenge
然后 challenge的结尾
and we'll know it's the end because we'll see a ret.
我们知道它是结尾，因为会看到一个 ret
Is this really a ret?
这真的是一条ret指令吗？
Actually, I haven't looked it up.
实际上 我还没查过
I usually try to not say things I don't actually know
我通常尽量不说我不知道的事
but I'd probably put money on
但我敢打赌
we talked about like pushes and pulls, right?
我们之前讨论过push和pop 对吧？
Pushes and pops, right?
push和pop 对吧？
So this seems wasteful because it's one instruction.
所以这看起来挺浪费的 专门设立一条指令
I believe this is just syntactic sugar for branch register X30
我相信这只是B X30寄存器的一个语法糖
but it's just much nicer to see the ret
ret更直观
because everyone is familiar with that.
因为大家都很熟悉
But this way, you don't have one instruction.
但这样，就没有单独的特殊指令
You have what looks to be one instruction to you
看着是一条特殊指令 但实际上……
but actually maps to a more complex function
但实际上它映射到一个更复杂的功能
that can branch to any of the 30 registers.
它可以跳转到 30 个寄存器中的任意一个
Okay.
好的
Cool, so let's go through the prologue here.
好的 我们看看这里的序言（应该是尾声）部分
So here, load pointer.(pair)
这里 ldp
So loading X29 and X30 from the stack pointer plus 160.
从栈指针加 160 的位置加载 X29 和 X30
Yeah, is this infix?
这是中缀表达式吗？
I think this is not infix.
我认为这不是中缀表达式
I think this doesn't change the value.
我认为这不会改变值
I think it changes it when it's outside
我觉得它在外部时才会改变值
like another example somewhere.
像某处的例子
Yeah, because this is, so basically
对 因为这样， 基本上
Wherever the stack currently is
不管当前栈的位置在哪
whatever stack pointer plus 160 is
不管栈指针加 160 是多少
take that memory location
取出该内存地址的值
put it into X29, and then at stack pointer plus 168
放入 X29 然后在栈指针加 168 处
move that into X30, and then
将它放入 X30 然后
increment the stack pointer by B0, filling up this stack frame.
将栈指针增加 0xB0 释放这个栈帧
I actually really hate how it doesn't do everything in hex.
我真的很讨厌，它不全用十六进制表示
This is driving me crazy.
这让我抓狂
I don't know if that's also for you all
不知道你们是不是也有同感
but if somebody finds a way to make...
但如果有人能找到方法让...
GDB and all these tools do that that would be amazing
GDB 和这些工具都用16进制表示 那就太好了
because I want
因为我
in all the instructions I just want to see hex
我只想看到十六进制的指令
Okay, so the stack frame
好的 栈帧
Cool okay, this is uh Yeah
酷 好的 就是这样
so this is exactly what I wanted to talk about here right
这正是我想讨论的
is that there's fundamental differences here between x86 64, right
是它和x86_64 存在根本区别 对吧
the fact that the return address is passed in a register is important
它通过寄存器传递返回地址 这点很重要
also the way that parameters are passed, right?
参数传递的方式也是这样 对吧？
By passing parameters through registers and all parameters
通过寄存器传递所有参数
I guess it's less very less similar to X32
这一点和x86 相差很大
where everything was passed on the stack.
在 x86 中 所有东西都是通过栈传递的
But yeah, so even having stack control
即便有了栈控制权
so setting up the
设置……
if you're trying to call a function and pass it arguments
如果你尝试ROP调用一个函数并传递参数
you need to use gadgets in order to put things
你需要使用一些gadgets
on the stack or from places you control into those registers
将数据从栈，或其它你能控制的地方，放入寄存器中
before you call that function.
再调用函数
Okay.
好的
And we talked about that.
我们已经讨论过它了
Yeah, so this is exactly what I wanted to show
对 这就是我要展示的
is that also the other thing that's crazy
另一个疯狂的地方是
is that different compilers are different.
不同的编译器编译结果也不同
This was not something I was prepared for before looking at this.
这是我之前没想到的
So, and maybe I'll...
所以 也许我会……
Oh, anyways, you'll find it in one of the challenges that I release later
哦 总之 你可以在稍后我发布的挑战中发现这一点
but I will compile these with a different compiler
但我将用不同的编译器编译这些代码
and you will see that like even the exact same source code
你会发现即使是完全相同的源代码
the overflow that you have to do is actually different
需要进行的溢出操作也会不同
because the compiler does weird things with how things are laid out.
因为编译器在布局上会搞一些奇怪的花样
So important things to remember of all of these, right?
所以 这里重要的是
Is, okay, where's my buffer on this stack?
目标缓冲区在栈上哪里？
How many bytes do I need to overwrite
我需要覆盖多少字节
to get to the saved frame pointer X29?
才能到达保存的栈帧指针 X29？
And then the next four
以及后面的四
next eight bytes will be the saved instruction point, program counter.
后面的保存着 程序计数器 的八个字节
In X30 and then that's where we want to go.
X30里的，就是要跳到的地方
I guess save link register.
大概叫保存的链接寄存器
It feels really weird calling it that.
这么叫它感觉很奇怪
And because we're trying to do exactly this part here.
我们想要做的，其实就是这部分
Okay, great.
好的 很好
Yeah, so this is
对 就是这个
there's one important thing.
有个重要的点
So, okay, this thing.
好吧 这个
Okay, we're almost done here with this part.
好的 这部分快完成了
So let's do...
那我们来...
So one of the most classic ROP...
这是最经典的 ROP 之一...
So for instance, we want to jump to this win function, right?
比如 我们要跳到这个 win 函数 对吧？
That's our goal.
这就是目标
Everyone agree here?
大家同意吗？
And when are other times?
其他时候呢？
So oftentimes we will not have just a win function.
很多时候 我们不会直接有一个win函数
But why would we want to jump to a whole function?
但为什么要跳转到整个函数呢？
Say again?
再说一遍？
Alignment?
对齐？
Eh, maybe.
嗯 可能吧
I think we can technically jump to any instruction.
我认为技术上可以跳转到任何指令
I think instructions are fine
我认为指令没问题
because there are four bytes.
因为这里有四个字节
I don't know if we can jump to halfway through an instruction.
我不确定能不能跳转到在一条指令的中间
I think that will cause a seg fault, I believe
我觉得这会导致段错误
or any other non-four offset into an instruction.
或者偏移不是四的倍数的指令
In any of your exploiting careers of targets
在你们攻击目标的职业生涯中
have you ever had to jump to a function or something?
你们有没有跳转到某个函数或类似的？
What was it?
是什么？
Execve?
execve？
Yeah, so jumping to ret to sys, ret to libc.
对 跳转到返回系统调用 返回到 libc
That's too many rets.
有太多可以ret了
But yeah, that whole idea of just returning to a specific function in the library
这个方法就是直接返回到库中的某个函数
that does what you want to do
这个函数能实现你的需求
that's great because you're reusing a whole chunk of thing
这样做很棒 因为你可以重用一大段代码
rather than building it up through little gadgets.
而不是通过gadget一点点构建
What other things?
还有其他方法吗？
Sometimes your overflow isn't enough to do anything super meaningful
有时候溢出的量不足以做太有意义的事
so you need to re-read and re-overflow some more.
所以需要再次读取 制造更多的溢出
Yeah, so it is if you're...
是的 如果你……
You may not have enough of a payload to generate a great ROP chain
你可能没有足够的载荷来生成一个高质量的 ROP 链
but if you can redirect control flow back to main
但如果能将控制流重定向回 main 函数
and get another right and maybe get several of them
再获得一次 甚至几次
you can build up a nice ROP chain.
你就能构建一个不错的ROP链
Yeah, that's a great example.
是的 这是个很好的例子
Yeah, so executing system calls, returning into libc
执行系统调用 返回到 libc
all that stuff is super important.
这些都非常重要
So let's go...
那么 开始...
I'm confident that you guys can all give input to this application
我相信你们都能给这个程序提供输入
in order to overwrite the saved link register X 30
覆盖保存的链接寄存器 X30
and then redirect control flow.
然后重定向控制流
So let's put ourselves in that mindset.
所以让我们进入这种思维模式
We have just, because I think it's really important.
我们强调这一点 是因为它真的很重要
One of the things that I always emphasize is like
我经常强调的一点是
you want to be able to kind of let's say
你希望能够做到 比如说
do this stuff in your head.
在脑子里完成这些操作
It doesn't have to be complete in your head.
不一定非得完全在脑中进行
I think it's totally fine to draw and do that.
我认为用画图或其他方法辅助完全没有问题
I do that all the time
我经常这样做
when I'm looking at things like exact offsets.
比如在查看精确偏移量等细节时
But being able to look at these instructions and
但能够查看这些指令并
walk through step-by-step exactly what's happening
逐步分析每一步发生了什么
so that you can be prepared for
以便做好准备
when you actually are running it against the real target
当你实际运行时
is super important.
这一点非常重要
And so, for instance
例如
let's say we're here.
假设我们在这一位置
We've probably done the overflow.
我们可能已经完成了溢出
We've changed here now X30 is
我们现在修改了 X30
where do we want to go?
我们想跳到哪里？
The win function.
win 函数
We want to win.
我们想获胜
So we want to go to the win function.
因此 我们想跳转到 win 函数
We put it into X30.
我们把它放到 X30 里
Now this instruction executes our stack pointer
现在这条指令操作栈指针
but it's incremented, cleaning up that whole thing.
增加了它，清理了整个栈帧
And we have the ret
然后是 ret
which is a branch to register X30.
这是一个跳转到寄存器 X30 的指令
That takes us to win.
这会带我们进入 win
All right.
好的
What's the first thing that happens at win?
在 win 里首先会发生什么？
So it stores X29
所以它存储 X29
whatever was in there
不管里面是什么
we controlled that because we must have controlled that because we
我们必须控制它
and actually that's another important thing
这其实是另一件重要的事情
when you're talking about overflows, right?
在谈论溢出时 对吧？
It's like, what did you overwrite and change?
你覆盖和改变了什么？
Because X29, if there had to be something special in there
因为 X29 里面可能有特别的东西
but so we're storing X29 and X30
我们在存储 X29 和 X30
and this is a cool way
这是一种很酷的方法
that you can see that like we're doing a ton of stack setup
你可以看到 我们通过一条指令就完成了
just in one instruction,
大量栈设置
Or function frame setup.
或者说函数栈帧设置
We are storing this X29 and X30, So this is
我们正在存储 X29 和 X30
I believe the prefix operator.
这是前缀操作符
So this will do a stack pointer minus 16
这会将栈指针减去 16
and then store at stack pointer at that current stack pointer
然后在当前栈指针位置存储
which is stack pointer minus 16.
即栈指针减 16 的位置
It'll store X 29
会存储 X29
and then eight bytes above that will store at stack pointer minus eight.
然后在栈指针减 8 处存储
Will store the
会存储 X30
so this was basically
所以这基本上
you can think of this as exactly equivalent to like push X 29.
你可以把它理解为类似于 push X29
No, I guess push X 30 and then push X 29.
不是 应该是先 push X30 再 push X29
注：括号后有!,会改括号里的寄存器。没有不改。
I have to diagram that out.
我得把这个画出来
But anyways, the semantics are x29 goes at stack pointer minus 16,
总之 X29 的位置是栈指针减 16
and then 8 bytes above that at stack pointer plus 8 is where x30 goes.
接着 X30 位于当前栈指针（-16后）加 8 的位置
Okay.
好的
But now the stack pointer is pointing right to x29 and x30, right?
现在栈指针指向了 X29 和 X30 对吗？
Everyone agree?
大家都同意吗？
Okay.
好的
The next instruction, what's the point of this instruction?
下一条指令 它的目的是什么？
Yeah, why?
嗯 为什么？
It's moving the stack pointer into the X29
它把栈指针移到了 X29
which is the frame pointer.
也就是帧指针
What was that?
什么？
Is it a leaf function?
这是叶函数吗？
No, because we're doing a lot of BLs here.
不是 因为这里有很多分支链接指令
This is great.
太好了
If I don't get good answers for you all
如果我不能给大家好的答案
I can just go to the chat(gpt).
我就可以去问gpt
It's like having a better smarter kid you can go to.
就像是有个聪明的孩子，可以去问
Yeah, it's just moving the base pointer down to where the stack pointer is.
对 就是把基指针移到栈指针的位置
Yes, so setting up the new function frame by setting up.
是的 通过设置新的函数帧来完成
So now this current function frame starts at
所以现在这个函数帧从
where the current stack pointer is.
当前栈指针的位置
Exactly.
对
Cool.
好极了
Okay, and I think actually your comment may actually be mostly...
好的 你们的评论可能大部分是...
It's not a leaf function because it's calling things
这不是叶函数 因为它在调用其他函数
but I think there's no local variables here
但我觉得这里没有局部变量
so it's not decrementing the stack pointer anymore
所以现在不再减少栈指针
to set up actually a space on the function frame.
来为函数帧分配空间了
And I believe, I don't know if it's 100%
我认为 虽然不确定是不是 100% 对
but I believe so that you can debug
但这样可以方便调试
and walk the stack back up
并且回溯整个调用栈
every function pointer should point exactly
每个函数指针都应该准确指向
where the other's function frame is.
其他函数的帧
So at your current X29
所以 你当前在 X29 处
If you dereference that memory location
如果解引用该内存位置
that should be your caller's X29
那应该就是调用者的 X29
and then all the way back up your call stack.
然后一路回溯到调用栈的顶部
And that allows you to walk that.
这就能让你遍历它了
And then you can know exactly where you came from
然后你就能准确知道你是从哪里来的
because that 29 plus eight is the stored link register.
因为 X29 加 8 就是存储的LR
So that's how you can walk the whole stack back up.
这样你就能遍历整个调用栈了
Okay, do we care what else happens here for exploitation purposes?
好了 我们还关心这里有没有其他可以利用的吗？
Not really, stuff happens, right?
不太关心 反正这里会发生一些事情 对吧？
This is all stuff that's like gonna happen in this function.
这些事情都会在这个函数中发生
It's target specific,
这是特定目标相关的
whatever, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
不管了 随便什么 巴拉巴拉
Okay, now we get to the good stuff at the end here.
好了 现在我们来看看最后这部分精彩内容
Now, what happens here?
现在 这里发生了什么？
So this is a post-fix operator.
这是一个后索引操作
So this is, yeah,
对 就是这样
so when it's
所以当它这样时
I guess the way to remember it is
我觉得记它的方法是
when it's inside like this
当立即数在括号里面
and there's a exclamation point
并且有个感叹号
it does the operation first.
它会先执行括号里的操作
If it's outside of this
如果立即数在外面
it does this operation because this makes sense of loading LDP X29 X30
它会执行这个 LDP X29 X30 [sp]
SP in brackets like this means dereference SP
SP像这样放在括号中，表示解引用 SP
load whatever the eight bytes that are there into X29
将 它里面的8 个字节加载到 X29 中
and the eight bytes above that into X30
将再上面 8 个字节加载到 X30 中
and then add 16 to it.
然后sp += 16
Okay, so we loaded that.
好的 已经加载好了
Now what happens?
接下来会发生什么？
When we do this ret, what happens next?
执行 ret 后 接下来会发生什么？
What was that?
什么？
X30. X29 is the frame pointer
X30. X29 是帧指针
Yeah, but what's in X30?
那 X30 里面是什么呢？
What was it?
是什么？
Why is it win?
为什么是 win？
Yeah, so we went right to win.
所以我们直接去了 win
So this will, when we return, go back here.
所以 当win返回时 会回到这里
And then what will happen when win returns?
那么 当 win 再返回时会发生什么？
Yeah, it will keep doing this forever.
是的 它会一直这样做下去
I think in this case you'll run out of file descriptors.
我觉得在这种情况下 你会用完文件描述符
You will open up every possible file descriptor for the flag.
会为flag打开所有可能的文件描述符
The flag will print out
flag会打印出来
and it will just keep printing this over and over again.
它会不断地重复打印这个，一遍又一遍
The reason why I'm telling you this now
我现在告诉你这一点
instead of letting you figure this out on your own is
而不是让你自己去发现
that I want you to be nice to our servers
是因为我希望你对我们的服务器友好些
and I don't want them to just do busy work for no stupid reason.
我不希望它们因为不必要的原因而做无用功
So if you can protect that.
所以请尽量避免这种情况
So this is the pitfall of returning to the start of a function
这就是返回到函数起点的隐患
And this is exactly because of the architecture saying that
这正是由于体系结构要求
jumping to like a function uses whatever's in that register.
跳转到函数时，直接使用寄存器中的内容
Well, how did you get there on a return?
那么 你是怎么通过ret到那里的
Because whatever is in there is in that register.
因为寄存器里的内容决定了跳转目标
Yeah, that's a great question.
是的 这是个很好的问题
I'm going to ask you.
应该我来问你
I don't have a lot of answers.
我没有什么答案
You're full of answers.
你们才有答案
What was it?
是什么？
Skip the first instruction.
跳过第一条指令
So what happens if we jump here?
那么 如果我们在这里跳转会怎么样？
Yeah , and then , so if we skipped and jumped to win plus four ,
是的 如果我们跳过并跳转到 win +4
move stack pointer into X29 ,
将栈指针移到 X29
and then do all the stuff ,
然后执行所有的操作
and then finally at the end , yeah
最后
so then go load from stack pointer plus 16 , oh sorry ,
从栈指针加 16 处加载 抱歉
from the stack pointer , load into X29 and then X30
从栈指针处加载到 X29 和 X30
So those were on the stack right above where the stack pointer is.
这些就在栈指针的上方
The stack pointer is actually getting
栈指针实际上会被
because it's here in this case
因为在这种情况下
it'll get popped off 16 bytes every time.
每次都会弹出 16 字节
So yeah, then we don't have to deal with the prologue
所以 我们就不需要处理序言了
This is the beauty of ROP, right?
这就是 ROP 的美妙之处 对吧？
Rather than having to go right to the start of a function,
不必从函数的起点开始
go to another point in the function
可以直接跳到函数的其他位置
and then you can generalize that concept
这样你就可以把这个概念推广开来
and go, well let's just skip that part where it's sourced on the stack.
我们可以跳过从栈中获取的那部分
This means that your payloads will be
这意味着你的攻击载荷会
very different than what you are used to in x86-64.
与你在 x86-64 上习惯的大不相同
This is part of why I think this is fun to do
这就是我觉得这很有趣的原因之一
because you have to get all of these offsets
因为你需要获取这些偏移量
of calling these functions correctly
并正确地调用这些函数
and they're going to do different things
这些函数会执行不同的操作
and it's going to be fun.
这将会很有趣
Cool.
好的
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
say it again
再说一遍
Yes, the stack pointer always has to be 16-byte aligned.
是的 栈指针必须始终 16 字节对齐
Yeah, so the way...
嗯 就是这样
I would probably...
我可能会...
I don't know the direct answer to your question.
我不能直接回答你的问题
My intuition is that every single one of these instructions
我的直觉是每个指令
has to leave the stack aligned correctly.
都必须使栈对齐
But even then, if ever that instruction was executed
但即使如此 如果某条指令被执行
the stack must be aligned properly
栈必须正确对齐
especially if you're executing an entire function.
尤其是当你执行整个函数时
Every single instruction has to leave the stack aligned correctly.
每条指令都必须保证栈正确对齐
So I think...
我觉得...
You don't need to worry about that.
你不用担心这个
Yeah, so that's on gadgets you would need to worry about that.
是的 用gadget时才需要担心这一点
Yeah.
是的
And if you're using a pushy pop style gadget
如果你用的是 push-pop 风格的gadget
you will need to do that.
你就得这样操作
Oh, let's look if...
哦 我们看看...
Did I install this?
我安装了吗？
Why does nothing work?
为什么什么都不行？
Okay.
好的
Okay, well it's going to be hard to not find any gadgets without any tools
好吧 没有工具 想找些gadget真挺难的
but we'll get that fixed.
但我们马上解决
There should be something here.
这里应该有点东西
Anyways, okay.
不管了 好的
Oh, this thing?
哦 这个？
Ah, there we go, okay.
啊 找到了 好了
I believe this has...
我觉得这个有……
Yeah, okay, great.
嗯 好的 太好了
It has support already for ARM.
它已经支持 ARM 了
If there's other stuff that's not installed, let me know.
如果还有其他没安装的 告诉我
I think I use Ropper usually or other stuff.
我通常用 Ropper 或其他工具
But anyways, so yeah, tons of weird gadgets.
不过 确实有很多奇怪的gadget
So you will have a fun time with this.
所以你会玩得很开心的
But that's the goal.
但这正是目标
Anything else?
还有其他事吗？
Okay.
好的
Let's break for five minutes
我们休息五分钟
because I've been going for over an hour.
因为我已经播了一个多小时了
Okay.
好的
I guess I'll pause the stream.
我先暂停一下吧
Do, do, do.
嗒 嗒 嗒
Now you can listen to music, Twitch stream.
现在可以听音乐了 Twitch 直播间
Or do I just stop streaming?
或者我直接停播？
I don't want to stop streaming.
我可不想停播
I'm just going to mute it.
我先把它静音
Okay.
好的
Hello, Twitch.
大家好 Twitch 直播间
I hope you enjoyed that break.
希望你们喜欢刚才的休息
I hope this stuff works.
希望这些能派上用场
We'll see.
咱们拭目以待吧
Actually, I have no idea if it's going to work,
其实 我也不确定这能不能行
but anyways it won't break right now.
总之，暂时不会出问题
I'll just fix it later.
到时候再修好了
Okay.
好的
So we did that.
所以搞定了
Let's do, because I don't know how long the CTF
我们 因为我不确定 CTF 能持续多久
the live breaking will work.
现场破解能成功吗
So let's shift gears
那我们换个话题
and go over to how to identify targets.
谈谈如何确定目标
Okay, we don't want to check, make sure here
好的 我们确认一下
whatever they can see presenter mode.
确保他们能看到演示模式
Okay, cool.
好的 可以
So why do we care about picking targets?
为什么我们要关心目标选择呢？
You might pick something
你可能会选择一些
where let's say the developers don't want you to find bugs in their stuff
开发者不希望你发现bug的东西
or vulnerabilities in their stuff.
或者他们产品的漏洞
Yeah, that's definitely true.
是的 确实如此
What else?
还有什么？
follow me okay
跟着我，好了
What else?
还有什么吗？
Some targets are easier than others?
有些目标比其他的好对付？
Why do you care about either of those things?
你为什么在意这些东西？
You want to find bugs?
你想找bug？
Finding bugs is easy.
找bug很简单
Look at your own code.
看看你自己的代码
You will find bugs.
你就能看到bug
Picking targets that are maybe more exploitable than others?
选择更容易被利用的目标？
Yeah, so...
嗯 所以...
What I want you to be thinking about, and I guess, I mean
我希望你们思考的 我想说的是...
I guess Yan talked about it a little bit
我想Yan已经提过一些
but so the background here is I spent a year
背景是我花了一年时间
doing basically vulnerability analysis,
做漏洞分析
targeting the XNU kernel and Mac.
目标是 XNU 内核和 Mac 系统
I didn't originally intend to target the kernel.
一开始我没打算针对内核
I wanted to do like Apple stuff.
我想做苹果的东西
And so I read a bunch of books about it
所以我读了很多相关书籍
and looked at user space programs and tried to
看了用户空间的程序 尝试
I think I was, D, not decompiling
我想我，不是反编译
but disassembling the kernel cache
而是反汇编内核缓存
which we'll get into,
我们之后会详细讲
but is basically like the kernel and every single driver in it.
但基本上就是内核以及里面的驱动
And I set that up
我把一切都设置好了
and it took literally like a day and a half in IDA to disassemble
我又花了一天半在 IDA 上反汇编
Anybody know?
有人知道吗？
Yeah, to even disassemble and create the control flow graph and everything.
是的 包括反汇编和生成控制流图
Does anybody know the trick?
有人知道这个技巧吗？
Or I think it used to be an older trick to speed up IDA
有个加速 IDA 的老技巧
It'd save you a long time
能节省很多时间
close like the console window
关闭控制台窗口
and all the other windows
以及其他所有窗口
because there's GUI refreshing that happens on like those side panels and stuff
因为那些侧边栏之类的会发生GUI刷新
and it speeds it up by like 30%.
这能提升大约 30% 的速度
It's like crazy stuff.
真是太神奇了
Anyways, so I spent a lot of time
总之 我花了好多时间
and what I'm trying to get through here is the lessons that I learned.
我想传达的是我学到的经验教训
So for those that don't know and aren't in academia, so sabbatical is...
对于不了解学术界的人来说 学术休假是...
Like, there's a specific thing in academia where every seven years
学术界有一种特殊的制度 每七年...
so your seventh year
也就是第七年
that's where seven comes from.
这就是‘七’的来源
Sabbath is similar to sabbatical.
学术休假和 sabatical 很类似
It has the same root.
词源相同
Every seven years, you can take time off
每隔七年 你可以休假
to go in different research directions or whatever.
去研究不同的方向或其他事情
That's, like, negotiated through your contract.
这通常是在合同中协商的
It's part of the reason why us academics put up with those lovely students
这是我们这些学者能够容忍那些淘气学生的部分原因
and our lack of pay compared to our industry peers
也是我们相比行业同行收入较低的原因之一
because we get a lot of freedoms.
因为我们有很多自由
And one of those freedoms is the ability to just like
其中一项自由就是可以
not have any university responsibilities for a year
一年不承担任何大学的职责
and be able to focus on other things.
能够专注于其他的事情
So I focused on bug finding and vulnerability analysis.
所以我专注于找漏洞和分析漏洞
And as part of that, some people
其中有些人
when they do a sabbatical, go and work at a company
休学术假时 会去公司工作
and make a bunch of money.
赚一大笔钱
And that's a great way to see what research problems like companies have.
这是了解公司在研究什么问题的好方法
And you get to make a salary because even though, you know
你还能拿到薪水 尽管
Your lovely tax dollars are paying my salary at ASU.
你们的税款支付了我在ASU工作的工资
Well, if you guys are working
嗯 如果你们在工作
I don't know if you're working, but the broader you.
我不知道你们是否在工作 但广义上的你们
And so the university will let you have that time off
所以大学会给你这段休假时间
but depending on your university
但不同大学情况可能不一样
you don't get full pay during that full time.
这段时间你拿不到全额工资
So my plan was I would make up my salary
所以我打算补足我的工资
by finding bugs and reporting bugs.
通过找漏洞和报告漏洞
That was the idea.
这就是我的打算
So this is something that I actually had to learn the hard way about
所以我是在实践中才慢慢学到这一点的
not just like what to target and why
不仅是选择什么目标，还有为什么要这样做
but i think i learned a lot about like
但我确实学到了很多
approaching it from the mindset of maximizing your money payout
如何从最大收益的角度来思考这个问题
which i did not think of as i was starting this
这是我刚开始时没想到的
i really only figured that out the last like three months
其实我是在过去的三个月才意识到这一点的
and then uh couldn't do anything with that information
然后不知道怎么用这些信息
um so this is why thinking about
所以才有了这些想法
because i spent months just poking around at like uh Mac OS,
因为我花了好几个月的时间在 Mac OS 上瞎摸
learning different things, but like not really
学了很多东西 但都没有深入
probably took like three months until I really like focused on the kernel
大概花了三个月 我才真正集中精力研究内核
and was like, okay
然后心想 好吧
I'm going to find this thing.
我要找到这个东西
But so I want you to
但我想请你
I want to talk about
我想谈谈
and I want us to discuss how to like pick, pick targets.
我还想和大家讨论如何选择目标
So one thing you can do is just randomly, right?
你可以随便选一个 对吧？
Just like pointed a thing.
比如随便找一个项目
Ah, there's a GitHub project.
啊 找到了个 GitHub 项目
I'm going to look for bugs and vulnerabilities in that target.
我打算在这个项目里找漏洞
Probably not effective.
可能不太有效
Right?
对吧？
Because just like random stuff may or may not
因为随便选的项目不一定有漏洞
you will find bugs by doing this.
你能找到漏洞
I absolutely guarantee you.
我绝对可以保证
If anybody, a good habit to do for bug finding is like reading code.
找漏洞的一个好习惯就是阅读代码
You can just read random source code.
你可以随便找些源代码来看看
If you do a Google, like not a Google search,
如果你用Google搜索，不对
a GitHub code search for just system.
你可以到 GitHub 上搜索有system的代码
and start looking at every C code that has system
然后查看所有包含system的 C 代码
you will absolutely find a vulnerability.
你绝对能找到漏洞
Or probably in Python, os.system
或者在 Python 的 `os.system` 中
you will absolutely find stuff.
你肯定能找到一些东西
There is stuff out there.
外面确实有些东西
You could, if you wanted to find real bugs in real systems
如果你想在实际系统中找真正的漏洞
you could do this for sure.
你这样做肯定行
You can choose what you know, right?
你可以选择你熟悉的东西 对吧？
What's the benefit of choosing software that you know?
选择熟悉的软件有什么好处？
What was it?
什么？
You already know what's in the code.
你已经知道代码的内容
Yeah, you already know, well, maybe the code.
对 你已经知道了 可能是代码
I mean, it depends on how really familiar you are with it, right?
这取决于你对它有多熟悉 对吧？
But it may be something you're very familiar with
但你可能非常熟悉
so you know how it works, right?
所以你知道它的运作方式 对吧？
That's a key thing of any kind of vulnerability analysis is
这是任何漏洞分析的关键
trying to identify and understand the target at a really deep level
即尝试识别并深入了解目标
so they can understand what are bad things.
以识别潜在问题
What's the downside of choosing what you know?
选择你熟悉的有什么坏处？
Say it again?
再说一遍？
Ah, the search stage becomes too small.
啊 搜索范围太小了
Yeah.
嗯
You know, if your daily driver is some Nix OS
你知道 如果你的日常系统是 Nix 系统
like if you find some Nix bug
比如你发现了一个 Nix 的 bug
I'm sure people will care, but like
我相信会有人关心 但是
would you want to find a bug in that or a bug in
你愿意在那个系统里找 bug 还是在
I don't know, Exchange server?
例如，Exchange 服务器里？
Anybody know what Exchange server is?
有人知道什么是 Exchange 服务器吗？
Anybody?
有人吗？
What's Exchange?
Exchange 是什么？
Yeah.
对
Email server.
邮件服务器
That's every, almost every large organization on earth
几乎所有的大型组织
uses exchange server to run their email.
都在用 Exchange 服务器来处理邮件
If they're either on Google or this basically.
如果他们用的是 Google 或类似的
And like, and exchange servers
还有 Exchange 服务器
do they have like an email server?
它们有邮件服务器
Does it have to be exposed to the internet?
它们必须暴露在互联网上吗？
Yeah, it has to.
是的 必须的
It collects messages.
它收集邮件
You find a bug where you can send an email to somebody's exchange server
你发现了一个漏洞 可以通过发送邮件到某人的 Exchange 服务器
and pop their exchange thing.
并入侵他们的 Exchange 服务器
You've taken over like multi-million dollar company's emails.
你就接管了市值数百万美元公司的邮件
That's like insane.
这太疯狂了
So this is part of some things to think about.
所以这是需要考虑的问题之一
Also, what's available?
还有 有哪些能使用到的？
What do you actually have access to, right?
你要能访问到的，对吧？
I mentioned Exchange,
我提到了 Exchange，
but anybody here have experience with Windows Server?
有人用过 Windows Server 吗？
Yeah?
嗯？
Do you have access to Exchange?
你能用 Exchange 吗？
Yeah, you have to have an MSDN subscription in order to install Exchange.
是的 需要 MSDN 订阅才能安装 Exchange
I think back in my day
依我以前的经验
students had access to MSDN and it was great
学生能用 MSDN 非常棒
but you need access to the software, right?
但你得有软件才行 对吧？
It would be super cool to find bugs in industrial control systems
在工业控制系统中找到漏洞会很酷
that do nuclear enrichment and all kinds of stuff
比如核浓缩和其他系统的漏洞
but like I don't know.
但我不知道
Do you have access to that stuff?
你能接触到那些东西吗？
If you do, don't say anything to me.
如果有的话 别告诉我
I don't want to know about it
我不想知道
but this is the kind of thing.
就是这样
What's available to you?
你有什么能接触到的？
You do have to think about this stuff
你确实需要考虑这些问题
because you can set your eyes on a target
因为你可能会定个目标
and then be like, okay, well, crap.
结果发现 完了 搞砸了
How do I get How do I run it?
我怎么得到它？怎么运行它？
And we'll talk about other things.
我们再聊点别的
Now, these are kind of, you know
现在 这些都是你知道的
one of the things, I mean
我是说 其中的一件事
what it really comes down to, honestly
说白了 就是
is you and your time, right?
就是你和你的时间 对吧？
If you're going to invest time in finding bugs
如果你打算花时间找 bug
like you should be thinking about
你应该好好想想
and I'll get there in a second
我马上要做了
like what do you want out of this,
你想要什么
right?
对吧？
And, you know, if you want to have an impact
如果你想产生影响
and you want to find bugs that are important that people care about
并找到那些重要且受人关注的 bug
anybody know of a named bug?
有没有人知道什么有名的 bug？
Of top of their head
马上能想到的
like a bug that has a name.
像是有名的漏洞
Heartbleed.
心脏出血
What are some other ones?
还有哪些？
What was it?
是什么？
Log4j.
Log4j
That was literally, does anybody know Log4j?
那不就是 有人知道 Log4j 吗？
Yeah.
对
Was anybody looking at bugs in the Java logging libraries
有人研究过 Java 日志库的漏洞吗？
that allowed arbitrary command execution
这些漏洞允许任意命令执行
that every company on earth freaked out about
让全球的公司都慌了
because every Java software uses logging and every
因为每个 Java 软件都会用到日志功能 每个
like so many companies use Java behind the scenes in their web services.
很多公司在他们的网络服务中都用到了 Java
Yeah, any other bugs, named bugs?
嗯 还有其他有名的漏洞吗？
Spectre, Meltdown?
幽灵， 熔断？
Yeah.
嗯
Huh?
什么？
Shell shock?
Shellshock？
Yeah, that was a great one.
嗯 那个确实很厉害
Yeah, so like, you know
嗯 你知道的
it's not that you necessarily, I wouldn't, oh, the question is
不一定非要这样做 我不会 哦 关键问题是
will we go over extracting firmware from real devices
我们会讨论如何从设备中提取固件吗？
and how to emulate it for VR purposes?
以及如何在虚拟现实中仿真它？
Absolutely not.
绝对不
That's something that you can do on your own.
这是你可以自己做的
The Zenbleed or the XZ Backstore was a great one.
Zenbleed 和 XZ Backstore 都很棒
And so it's important to consider something to think about.
所以考虑一下还是很重要的
You have limited time. Where are you going to spend your time?
时间有限 你打算把时间花在哪里？
Is it on something important?
是在重要的事情上吗？
I'm not saying you should find bugs.
我不是说你应该去找漏洞
I'm not even saying
我也不是说
that I like these weird named bug things.
我喜欢这些奇怪命名的 bug
I think it's kind of a weird trend
我觉得这是一股奇怪潮流
but I don't know.
但我也不清楚
I understand why people do it.
我能理解为什么有人这么做
But that's like
但就像
do you want to spend your weekends or your life finding bugs in...
你愿意花上周末或一生，
Game Boy emulators?
找游戏机模拟器上的 bug吗？
I don't know.
我不知道
Like, it's cool. It's cool.
真的挺酷
But, you know.
但是你知道
Availability, like we talked about, right?
获取的方便性 就像我们之前说的 对吧？
Can I get my hands on that thing?
我能弄到那东西吗？
Can I run that thing?
我能运行那东西吗？
This is honestly, I will try to abstract this as much as possible
说实话 我会尽量简化这个问题
but this is the main thing that's a pain of doing XNU research.
但这确实是进行 XNU 研究的难点
Because, like, especially with the ARM
因为 特别是 ARM 处理器
And the Apple Silicon Macs
还有苹果芯片
they have locked down access to these systems so much that like loading
他们对这些系统的访问限制得非常严格 以至于加载
because on the Intel Macs
因为用Intel芯片 的 Mac
you can load alternative kernels and stuff.
你可以加载其他内核等
So loading a like a KASAN kernel
比如加载有 KASAN 的内核
which has address sanitizers to prove
它有地址检查器来证明
that you found some out of bounds write
你发现的越界写问题
because you can get a case and report
因为你可以得到一个用例和报告
that you could use in your bug report to Apple
它能用在你给苹果的bug报告中
is super important.
这非常重要
But like I had to use separate machines.
但我不得不使用单独的机器
Like I had kept an old laptop around for that.
我一直留着一台旧笔记本用于这个
Like people buy other machines for this and it's a pain.
人们为此要买其他设备 确实麻烦
Yes, Chad is very good.
是的 查德真的很牛
Weird names are at least more recognizable than CV numbers.
奇怪的名字至少比简历编号好记
Absolutely agree, which is why that's, I think, cool.
完全同意 我觉得这点很酷
Money, right?
钱 对吧？
If you're gonna be spending your time, there's...
你要花时间 就得……
Oh, wow, I should have had a whole slide on ethics.
哦 天哪 我应该用一整张幻灯片来讲伦理
We should probably just talk about that next.
我们接下来就讨论这个
Yeah, well, maybe, I mean
嗯 也许 我是说
I like learning stuff
我喜欢学习
but when I say money, I mean
我说的钱就是指
this was like literally my reality
这是要面对的现实
where I had to hypothetically feed myself by the bugs that I found.
我得靠找到的bug来养活自己
And so that can affect what target you choose.
这会影响你选择的目标
Does the Game Boy emulator have a bug bounty program?
Game Boy 模拟器有漏洞赏金计划吗？
I mean, maybe, I don't know.
可能有吧 我不知道
I don't write Game Boy emulators
我不写 Game Boy 模拟器
but they probably don't.
但他们可能没有
Yeah, exactly.
对 没错
And what is that bug bounty program like?
那个漏洞赏金计划是怎样的？
How often are people paid?
人们多久领一次酬劳？
What do you know about that?
你对这个了解多少？
Do you know anybody that's getting paid by that?
你知道有人靠这个挣钱吗？
The other thing, this isn't a word
还有一点 这不是一个词
but I think maybe you probably know this.
但我认为你们可能知道这个
It's kind of similar to availability.
它有点像可用性
How easy is it to debug this thing?
调试这个东西容易吗？
Is it such a pain that it makes you want to rip your hair out?
这会让人痛苦到想抓头发吗？
On one hand, that can actually be a benefit
一方面 这实际上是个优势
because it's a bit of a moat, right?
因为这有点像护城河 对吧？
If you think like nobody else is probably popping that target
如果你觉得没人会去碰这个目标
because it's such a pain to debug
因为调试太麻烦了
and figure out what's going on.
还要搞清楚发生了什么
But if it takes you a month
但如果你花了一个月
to go from I know this bug exists to creating an exploit
才从发现漏洞到创建利用
or doing something that you can demonstrate to the bug banning program
或者展示给漏洞赏金计划
or whatever you're doing
或你在做的事情
That's a lot of time that you're not finding other bugs, right?
这一大段时间你都没在找其他漏洞 对吧
You're maybe learning a lot, which is great.
不过你可能学到了很多 这挺好的
I guess I should have thought of like learning stuff.
也许我应该多考虑学习这些东西
Ah, great.
啊 挺好
The question on here
问题来了
how do companies like Raytheon
像雷神这样的公司
or other defense contract companies decide on targets?
或其他国防承包商是如何确定目标的？
Yeah, they do not decide targets.
没错 他们不决定目标
So there are, let's talk about
那么 我们来谈谈
I'm just going to make a slide so I can fill it in later.
我先做个幻灯片 一会儿再填内容
See, JIT is not just for compilers.
看，JIT 不仅能用在编译器上（哈哈）
Okay.
好的
So, ethics, don't go to jail.
所以 道德 不要进监狱
This is what I always tell the 365 students.
这是我常对 365 学生说的
I'm actually not worried about any of the 365 students going to jail.
我其实不担心 365 班的学生会坐牢
They learn not quite enough to even be dangrous
他们学得还不够多 不足以造成危险
and the ones that do do know how to do things are usually smart enough
那些知道怎么做的通常也足够聪明
where they're not gonna go to jail.
他们不会去坐牢
And for here, specifically we're talking about vulnerability research.
在这里 我们说的是漏洞研究
This is like finding bugs in software, right?
这就是在软件中找漏洞 对吧？
You need to be able to have it.
你需要能够拥有它
You need to be able to run it on your own machine.
你需要在自己的机器上运行它
Never do this on a production real system.
永远不要在生产系统上做这件事
That's just like absolutely crazy
那简直太疯狂了
unless it's part of the parameters of the bug bounty program.
除非它是漏洞赏金计划的一部分
Facebook is very good about this.
Facebook 在这方面做得很好
They have a completely separate
他们有一个完全独立的
social network and testing system that you can do everything on there
社交网络和测试系统 你可以在那里做任何事情
and as long as you use that
只要你使用这些系统
you can test their like basically test production system um
你就可以测试他们近乎真实的生产系统
and then so the question is then what happens when you find something
那么 找到了什么之后，做什么
so you find a bug it's an exploitable bug
当你发现一个可利用的漏洞时
you've written either a proof of concept i guess
你编写了概念验证（PoC） 我想
what's the difference between a proof of concept and an exploit
PoC和攻击利用有什么区别？
Yeah, a little bit tricky.
嗯 这个问题有点复杂
I wouldn't necessarily say that a proof of concept shows that it's exploitable.
我未必会说 PoC 能证明漏洞能被利用
It shows that the bug exists
它证明了这个漏洞确实存在
and that it's probably a real bug.
而且很可能是一个真正的漏洞
Whether it's exploitable depends on your goals
它是否可以被利用取决于你的目的
and it's one of these things like it could be exploitable
而且这种漏洞可能需要
chained with other things, right?
和其他漏洞结合后才能被利用 对吧？
Or there's a lot of mitigations in place, but, you know.
或者有很多缓解措施在起作用 不过你知道的
like
比如说
so but taking that step from like this is a proof of concept
所以 从PoC
something that triggers a bug that a developer can use to identify that bug and fix it
一个能触发bug，方便开发者找到并修复问题的东西
to a full exploit chain that actually achieves control
到构建一个完整的利用链 实现控制
is there's a ton of like variants in there and difference
这里面有很多变化和不同
we'll try to learn as much as we can
我们会尽量多学
because i think that's interesting of like how systems work
因为我觉得了解系统的工作原理很有趣
of how to build like an exploit chain and these kinds of things
以及如何构建利用链这些事也很有趣
uh that's also what you know
你也是知道的
i want i want to find find
我想找到
and not just find things
不仅是发现这些问题
but exploit things that's the fun thing
还能利用这些问题 这才是真正有趣的地方
okay
好的
so then So what are your options?
那接下来 你有哪些选择呢？
So you found a bug.
所以你发现了一个漏洞
You want to get paid.
你想拿到报酬
What are some things that you guys have heard of to get paid?
大家都知道哪些方法可以拿到报酬？
Yeah, you make a proof of concept.
对 你可以做个概念验证
Let's say you have that.
假设你已经有一个了
You have that in your hand.
你手头有这个了
Yeah, so there's different types of bug bounty programs.
是的 漏洞赏金计划有多种类型
There can be You can think of outsourced bug bounty programs
可以是外包的漏洞赏金计划
where the company itself doesn't run it, but another one like HackerOne
公司不直接运营 而是由像 HackerOne 这样的第三方来运行
or one of these other sites has a bug bounty program.
或者由其他类似平台运营的漏洞赏金计划
And it could be an in-house bug bounty program that is run by the company.
也可能是公司自己运营的内部计划
I believe, I don't know for certain
我认为 但不敢确定
but I think Microsoft was one of the first companies to do a bug bounty program.
微软可能是最早推出漏洞赏金计划的公司之一
And so companies do this.
所以很多公司都会这样做
So you have the – you find the bug.
所以你发现漏洞
You report the information to the company.
你把信息报告给公司
I don't know.
我不知道
What happens next?
接下来会发生什么？
They fix it, hopefully, right?
他们应该会修复它 对吧？
So you can –
所以你可以——
so, yeah, they will – almost always attempt to fix it
是的 他们几乎总是会尝试修复它
this is like a whole thing of like how much time do you give them to fix it
这就像一个问题——你需要给他们多长时间来修复它
and if they're dragging their feet
如果他们拖拖拉拉
the theory there is like you're not that smart
理论上——你并不聪明绝顶
so if you found it
所以 如果你发现了
somebody else better and smarter than you has already found it
比你更聪明的人可能也已经发现了它
and maybe actually weaponizing it
甚至可能会将其用作武器
and using it against people
用来对付别人
so it's better than everyone knows it's a problem
所以最好大家都知道到这个问题
um Yeah, it's a whole thing.
嗯 这确实是个问题
I don't want to get into all this of bug bounty.
我不想讨论漏洞赏金的事
We can talk about that later, I think.
我们之后再讨论这个吧
But basically, so you can report to the company
但基本上 你可以向公司报告
and you know it's highly likely that it gets fixed.
你知道它很可能会被修复
And they will often
他们通常会
depending on their bug bounty program
根据他们的漏洞赏金计划
give you some money.
给你一些钱
Now, the next, let's say on the ethics spectrum
接下来 我们来看看道德光谱上的一个例子
this is my opinion
这只是我的看法
I will be telling you.
我来告诉你们
I hope you think... that that is reasonable, but you know, whatever
希望你们觉得这合情合理 不过 随你们怎么想吧
you're your own people.
你们自己拿主意
I'm not gonna control how you think.
我不会干涉你们的想法
So kind of the next step over is companies like, who does Pwn2Own?
再下一个层次 就是像举办 Pwn2Own 的公司 你们知道是谁吗？
ZDI, yeah, ZDI.
ZDI 对 就是 ZDI
So why does ZDI pay for bugs?
那么为什么 ZDI 会给漏洞付费呢？
Does anybody know?
有人知道吗？
Wait, let me go over here.
等等 我过去一下
Why?
为什么？
You've been to Pwn2Own and done this.
你参加过 Pwn2Own 而且做过这个
You've gotten money from this company.
你从这家公司拿过钱
You don't know why they give you money?
你不知道他们为什么给你钱？
Okay, if anybody gives you money
如果有人给你钱
you should know why.
你应该知道为什么
This is a general life thing.
这是生活常识
This is literally why we're talking about ethics here.
这就是我们在这里讨论伦理的原因
That part I don't know.
那部分我不清楚
I think, yeah, partly
我觉得是的 部分确实如此
but a lot of those targets they don't necessarily work with them.
但很多目标并不一定与他们合作
And you can do it outside of Pwn2Own and sell bugs to them.
你也可以在 Pwn2Own 之外发现漏洞并出售给他们
you know,
你知道
a marketing aware
市场营销方面的考虑
So they specifically at least the way they were created
至少在创建时 他们
they were with an antivirus company.
是与一家杀毒公司合作的
So they would take the exploits that they would buy
他们会购买这些漏洞利用
they would write signatures that they could push out to their AV system
编写签名并推送到防病毒系统
and say that they have basically pre-zero day detection of these bugs.
并声称可以检测这些未公开漏洞
And then they would work with, probably concurrently then
然后他们会，通常会同时
report the bugs and work with them too.
报告并协助修复这些漏洞
Right, yes.
对 没错
Trend Micro, ZDI
趋势科技的ZDI项目
Exactly.
没错
Yeah, they put it in their product, but they also
是的 他们会把这些加入产品中 但还会
I think mainly what the guys are saying is
我觉得他们主要是想说
they just get to put the numbers in their presentations
他们可以将这些数字放在演示中
like we found or we...
比如我们发现或协助修复了……
you know, facilitated the fixing of 30 critical, say, zero days.
比如说 协助修复了 30 个关键的零日漏洞
You've got millions of dollars.
你们有几百万美元
You've got the largest competition in the world.
你参加的是世界上最大的比赛
So, yeah,
所以 是的
I think it's going to be a marketing thing.
我觉得这会是个营销手段
And they still get money in the balance.
而且他们还是有收入的
Like, if they train a Chromebook
比如 如果他们培训了 Chromebook 用户
they still get value.
他们还是能获得价值
Interesting.
有趣
But the money they give you is more than the Chromebook.
但他们给你的钱比Chromebook 多
Oh, yeah.
哦 对
It's like double.
差不多是两倍
Exactly, yeah.
没错 就是这样
So they're making money.
所以他们是在赚钱
Somebody's getting paid some way, right, through this stuff.
总有人会通过这些赚到钱 对吧？
So it's important to remember.
所以记住这一点很重要
So that's also if you notice in the spectrum we will walk down.
如果你注意到，在我们要继续讲的变现方法中
The money that you can get paid for this.
你能从这当中赚到的钱
I think the good
我觉得好的一点是
the thing I like to go with is like
我是这么想的……
I think the point
我觉得重点在于
actually maybe have I increased it, but anyways
可能我夸大了 不过总之
when I was doing this stuff, a fully remote exploit for the iPhone
我弄的时候，有个 iPhone 的完全远程漏洞利用
that's zero click
是一个0交互的漏洞利用
meaning absolutely no interaction.
意味着完全不需要用户互动
So you send a text message
所以你给用户发送一条短信
or something to the user's device
或是其他东西到用户的设备
and it completely takes over the device all the way to the kernel.
然后它会完全接管设备 一直渗透到内核
So complete root level, well, no, actually, I mean
所以是完全的 root 级别， 不对 我是说
we'll get this on Mac.
我们谈到 Mac 时会提到
Root is not the final word.
Root 并不是终点
It's actually kernel access
它只是拿到了内核访问权
because of all the system integrity protection
因为系统有各种完整性保护
and stuff that's on there.
以及其他各种保护
But that's a million dollars.
但这价值一百万美元
So Apple themselves will give you a million dollars for that.
所以苹果会为此支付一百万美元
I actually don't know if anybody's done this yet.
实际上我不知道是否有人已经做到了
I don't know.
我不知道
Because that's like that chains like
因为它链接了一串漏洞
I don't know, so many bugs together.
我不知道 这么多漏洞组合在一起
It's like it's hard to even think about.
简直让人难以想象
But, and if you send that to somebody like ZDI
但如果你把它发给，比如 ZDI
they will give you much more than that.
他们会给你更多的钱
I don't know exactly how much more.
我不知道具体能多多少
You can see all of this.
这些你都能看到
Then you get into, let's say
接下来 比如说
and I'm not trying to offend anyone.
我不是要冒犯任何人
There's different steps.
有不同的步骤
So then, okay, we're in the United States right now,
所以 我们现在都在美国
at least everyone in this room.
至少在场的每个人都是
You could sell this
你可以卖掉这个
you could sell that information to a government
你可以把这信息卖给政府
let's say that you trust
比方说 你信任的某个政府
like the U.S. government has a
比如美国政府，就有一个
I think it's VRP is what they call it.
他们称之为 VRP
Vulnerability Research Program or something like that a reporting program
漏洞研究或报告项目
where you can sell this vulnerability to the US government
你可以在这些项目中把漏洞卖给美国政府
they actually have a system in place
他们有一套系统
to decide if they should disclose it to the vendor
来决定是否告诉供应商
and get it fixed or if they use it operationally
修复漏洞或者在行动中使用
and never disclose it to the vendor
永远不告诉供应商
so that's up to you and your personal ethics
这由你个人的道德标准决定
whether you're okay with your stuff being used by the US government
你是否接受自己的东西被美国政府使用
then there are Further than that
还有更进一步的
I actually don't know exactly how much that pays.
实际上我并不清楚这能赚多少钱
I haven't actually done any, you know
我实际上还没做过这些 你知道的
I stuck just to the reporting to Apple, just to be very clear.
我只是向苹果报告漏洞 非常明确
And so then the next step beyond that is basically, well
然后接下来的步骤基本上是
I guess there's two more-ish SAPs.
我想还有两个类似的程序
The next one will be reporting it to a company
下一个就是向一家公司报告
that will pay you a ton of money
他们会给你一大笔钱
and will never tell you who they're selling it to
而且永远不会告诉你他们把漏洞卖给谁
or where it's being used for.
或用在哪里
So you have absolutely no control over what governments
所以你完全无从控制，是卖给哪个政府
or things that are buying that
或是购买这些信息的其他机构
and you are getting paid to keep silent about the stuff that you found.
而给你的钱包括了封口费
And then the even one beyond that is dealing directly
更进一步 可能直接面对那些
with what some of you would probably consider a hostile foreign government
一些人可能认为是敌对的外国政府
that buys this stuff to use against their citizens
这些政府会购买这些信息用来针对他们的公民
or journalists or all this kind of stuff.
或记者等人群
So anyways, it's very important to understand.
所以 了解这些很重要
what you are doing and in what context it could be used
你在做什么 以及你的漏洞会在什么情况下使用
so that you are comfortable.
这样你才会安心
For instance, if you just think, ah
比如 你可能心想 啊
I'm a cool hacker
我是个酷黑客
I like finding stuff, I love CTFs
我喜欢找东西 特别喜欢 CTFs
I love this real world
我喜欢这个真实世界
an actual real world CTF
一个真正现实中的 CTF
I've got this exploit against the iPhone, this is awesome
我有一个针对 iPhone 的漏洞 太棒了
I don't want Apple's million dollars
我不想要苹果的那一百万
I want $10 million
我要 1000 万美元
or $15 million
或者是 1500 万美元
or whatever the price on the street is for a zero-click remote iPhone exploit.
或别的黑市上0交互远程 iPhone 漏洞的价格
And then you find out
然后你发现
that Google Project Zero does a teardown of your exploit
Google Project Zero 对你的漏洞利用进行了分析
where they caught it being used against
他们发现该漏洞被用来针对
I don't know, a vulnerable population in China, for instance.
比如说 中国的某个易受攻击群体
I don't know
我不知道
you have to live with that the rest of your life.
你这辈子都得背着这个
So think about the decisions that you're making, make right decisions.
所以 三思而后行 做出正确的决定
Oh, and then somebody, sorry
哦 对不起 有个人
the whole reason why we got onto this
我们讨论这个话题的原因是
somebody asked about defense contractors.
有人提到了国防承包商
So one of the jobs you can get for doing vulnerability research
你可以通过漏洞研究获得的工作之一是
especially in the United States
尤其是在美国
if you can get a clearance
如果你能获得安全许可
is with a company that does vulnerability research and finding bugs there
为一家专门研究漏洞的公司工作
you do not define the target.
你不会指定目标
The US government defines the target and tells you
美国政府会指定目标并通知你
find us bugs in here
在这里找到漏洞
and find us exploits and vulnerabilities in here.
并在这些地方发现利用手段和漏洞
And your job in that company is cranking that stuff out.
在那家公司 你的任务就是不断完成这些工作
So that's, I'm happy to talk with people.
所以我很愿意和大家聊聊
I've talked to some people in this line of work.
我跟这行的一些人交流过
It can be very demoralizing
这份工作可能会让人很沮丧
because you don't get to choose the target
因为你没有选择目标的权利
and it's just like given to you.
目标都是分配给你的
So it may not be interesting
所以这些工作可能没什么意思
but somebody thinks it's important enough to pay for you to do that
但有人觉得足够重要 愿意为此付费
so i don't know all right
我也不好说
cool any ethics questions act ethically please
好的 有什么伦理问题吗？请大家遵守伦理规范
all right
好的 没问题
oh cool corporate bug finding great we did this all right
哦 不错 公司找bug 我们讲完了
awesome
太好了
okay so is working with defense contractors ethical
那么 和国防承包商合作算不算道德呢
i will not touch that
这个问题我不评论
that's again I think
我认为
you need to make your own decisions about what is or is not ethical in your mind.
你得自己判断是否道德
Okay.
行
So you've decided on a target.
所以你已经选好目标了
I would say one of the biggest flaws that I ran into
我觉得我遇到的最大问题之一是
that some of you may also
你们可能也会遇到
is to resist the temptation to just dive right in and find bugs.
就是如何抵制，直接跳进去找漏洞的诱惑
Like you've been doing pwn college
你一直在做pwn college
you've been doing CTFs
你一直在参加 CTF
you just want to like find bugs.
你只想找到漏洞
You can do that, but
你可以这样做 但是
and you'll find stuff
你会找到一些东西
but it's much better to take time to plan it out.
但花时间好好规划会更好
Right, like how am I going to find these bugs?
对 我该怎么找到这些漏洞？
What tools am I going to use?
我打算用什么工具？
Am I gonna use static analysis?
我打算用静态分析吗？
Am I gonna use symbolic execution?
我会用符号执行吗？
Am I gonna use fuzzing?
我会用模糊测试吗？
I will tell you if you can use fuzzing, use fuzzing.
能用模糊测试就用
Fuzzing is absolutely hands down the best way to find bugs in anything.
模糊测试绝对是找 Bug 的最佳方法
Like you want to make money doing this stuff
你想靠这行赚钱的话
the best thing you can do
你能做的最好就是
find an important target that pays money
找一个能赚钱的重要目标
figure out what the important components are of that target
弄清楚目标的重要部分
that maybe pays you more.
也许能赚更多
This is again, kind of a metagaming thing.
这又是一个策略上的事情
and then figure out how to fuzz that thing.
然后弄清楚怎么对那个目标进行模糊测试
Like, AFL++ is great.
AFL++ 真不错
Use it.
用它
Fuzz stuff.
做模糊测试
It finds stuff.
它能发现问题
It's amazing.
它真的很厉害
Yeah.
嗯
Other things to think about.
还有其他需要考虑的
This is something that
这是只有在……
until it's bit you in the butt
你碰到问题之后
you won't actually really think about
你才会考虑的
especially if you're doing static analysis or...
特别是在做静态分析时 或者...
Oh, the question is, why is fuzzing the best?
问题来了 为什么模糊测试最好？
Fuzzing is the...
模糊测试是...
I mean, I have a lot of stories about this
这个我能讲很多
but fuzzing is the best because it's
但模糊测试是最好的 因为它
A you get a result that is
首先 你能得到一个结果
if it's a reproducible crash
如果是可重现的崩溃
you get an input that causes a crash in the target.
你会得到一个导致目标崩溃的输入
And that's like absolutely critical
这非常重要
because then you can debug the root cause
因为这样你就可以调试根本原因
figure out what's going on.
搞清楚是怎么回事
And you can think of like
你可以这样想
so when I was doing the XNU stuff
在我研究 XNU 的时候
I was harnessing different things.
我使用了不同的方法
And when I created
当我创建时
which is basically like, letting the fuzzer target that specific system.
基本上是让模糊测试工具针对那个特定的系统
So I gave the fuzzer this one subsystem I was fuzzing.
所以我让模糊测试工具针对这个子系统
I think it was the PF
我记得是 PF
which is the packet filter, like before eBPF, like the E part,
它是数据包过滤器 在有 eBPF 以前
just the BPF, the firewall component.
只有 BPF 部分，它就是防火墙的组件
There's two different devices that you can talk to it from.
有两个不同的设备 你可以通过它们通信
It was like dev PF and dev PFM.
就像 /dev/PF 和 /dev/PFM 这样的设备
And then where that went into the kernel code
然后等进入到内核代码中
it could select which one that came from.
它可以区分这些请求来自哪个设备
And I was harnessing it.
我当时就利用了这一点
I'm like, sure, whatever.
我心想 好吧 随便
I'll let the fuzzer decide which one.
我让模糊测试器来决定是哪一个
Thinking in my mind, like
我心里想
this is stupid because how could that ever make a difference?
这太蠢了 这怎么可能有区别？
Like, I don't even understand what these two different things are.
我甚至不明白这两个东西是什么
I still don't understand what they are
我到现在还是不明白它们是什么
but the fuzzer found a use after free bug by creating something on one
但模糊测试工具找到了一个UAF漏洞，通过在一个地方创建了一个对象
and then deleting it on the other
然后在另一个地方删除了这个对象
and then accessing it from the other one.
接着从另一个地方又访问了这个对象
And like, without giving it that thing
而且 根本没给它那个东西
like I never would have in a hundred years.
我这辈子都想不到
thought that that could have possibly been a bug.
那竟然可能是个 Bug
Like I grabbed the source code
我找了源代码
and I looked for these differences
找了找这些差异
and I couldn't like see it right away.
我没能看出来
And so I was just like, yeah, whatever.
所以 我就想 算了
I'd be like
我就会这么说
let the fuzzer figure it out.
让模糊测试器搞定吧
So even if the fuzzer is like smartly using a lot of input combinations
所以即使模糊测试器用了多种输入组合
to generate crazy inputs.
来生成奇怪的输入
So yeah, anyways, it's great.
所以 总之 挺好的
Okay.
好的
One thing that can, that especially
有一件事尤其要注意
so we've talked about exchange, right?
我们讨论过 Exchange 了 对吧？
People configure systems, right?
人们会配置系统 对吧？
And oftentimes code is gated by that configuration.
而且代码经常受限于这些配置
So if you spend three or four months finding a bug in Microsoft Exchange
所以如果你花了三四个月的时间，找到一个 Microsoft Exchange 的漏洞
and then by the end you say, oh crap
到最后你才发现 糟糕
this is only a real bug if this configuration is activated
这只有在激活了这个配置时才是个真正的漏洞
and it's a setting that nobody uses.
而这是一个几乎没人用的设置
I don't know
我不知道
is that an important bug?
这算不算重要的漏洞？
maybe maybe not but you probably wasted a lot of time
可能重要 也可能不重要 但你大概浪费了不少时间
this is a really good thing for like doing pwn2own in these types of uh competitions
这对参加pwn2own 这类比赛也很有帮助
because you need to make sure that the stuff you're testing
因为你需要确保你测试的内容
is the actual stuff that's going to be wrong
是确实会出问题的地方
okay cool
好的 真酷
we're flying by okay all right
进展顺利 很好
very important to play the metagame
对技术外的思考非常重要
this is something i did not understand until the end of it
这一点我直到最后才明白
because i spent um uh
因为我花了很多时间
I spend a lot of time just looking for bugs and having fun
找漏洞 玩得很开心
and it wasn't until the end I was like, oh, duh, well
直到最后我才反应过来 哦 原来如此
Apple pays more for bugs that are more impactful, right?
苹果公司会为更有影响力的漏洞支付更高 对吧？
So like, oh, I guess I should have said the million-dollar thing.
所以 哦 我应该强调一下那个百万美元的漏洞
Obviously, I did not win a million dollars
显然 我没赢得一百万美元
or maybe if I did
或者如果我赢了
I wouldn't be here teaching you right now.
我就不会在这里教你了
I'd be relaxing
我会很轻松
and, I don't know, retired and, I guess, living the good life.
我可能会退休 过上悠闲的生活吧
But... They pay different levels depending on what the impact is, right?
但是……他们会根据漏洞的影响支付不同的报酬 对吧？
So just like we said, so on XNU on the Mac platform
正如我们所说 在 Mac 平台的 XNU 中
there's a difference between root and kernel.
root 和 kernel 之间有区别
So root does not have full permission to the system.
所以 root 没有系统的全部权限
So I think actually
所以实际上
like I made the mistake
我犯了一个错误
where a lot of the stuff I was fuzzing and testing
我做的很多模糊测试
could only be done by the root user.
都只能由 root 用户执行
which meant that the bugs that I found were root to kernel bugs
这意味着，我找到的漏洞都是从root根权限到内核级别的
which are still bugs, and they paid
也是漏洞 也都获得了报酬
but not as much as if it was a user space, like from a regular user
但报酬比能从普通用户触发的漏洞 要少
or from even better, an iPhone app,
或者更好是能 从 iPhone 应用触发
from an iPhone app to the kernel and then a kernel bug.
从 iPhone 应用到内核 再到内核漏洞
That would have paid way better.
这种漏洞的报酬要高得多
And I didn't think about that to the very end.
我直到最后才想到这一点
And then I started, actually
然后 实际上我开始着手了
I actually have an example we'll go into here, but...
其实我有一个例子 我们接下来会讲到 但……
Yeah, I didn't do that until the very end.
是的 我直到最后才那么做
And then by that point
到了那时候
I didn't have much time
我没多少时间了
and I had to go back to school and everything.
我要回去教学了
So, but by metagaming
所以 通过玩元游戏（跳出盒子思考）
part of this is like
其中的一部分是
what other bugs have people found in this target, right?
其他人在这目标上发现了什么漏洞 对吧？
So read write-ups.
所以要读相关报告
I know it sounds simple
我知道这听起来很简单
but like there are people that write about and talk about these targets.
但是确实有人会写和讨论这些目标
What other bugs have they found?
他们还发现了哪些漏洞？
How did they find those bugs?
他们是怎么发现这些漏洞的？
Like build on other people's tools.
比如借用别人的工具
If you can do it
如果能做到
don't reinvent the wheel and build your own tools.
就不要重复造轮子 自己开发工具
If you can, like if somebody's got a fuzzer for a target
如果有人已经为某个目标开发了模糊测试工具
and it fuzzes component A, ask yourself
这个工具可以测试组件 A 你可以问自己
how can I just make it fuzz component B
我怎么让它测试组件 B
and then C and then D?
接着是 C 再是 D？
And guess what?
猜猜看
If nobody's done that before
如果之前没人这么做过
you'll find bugs.
你会发现漏洞
Like fuzzers shake out and find bugs all the time.
模糊测试工具经常能发现漏洞
Very important thing.
这非常重要
What bugs pay the most?
哪些漏洞的回报最高？
If you're going to spend the time on it
如果你要花时间在这上面
what bugs pay the most for your target?
在你的目标上 哪些漏洞的回报最高？
So for me, what I finally did was look at like, okay
所以 我最终决定查看 好吧
what kernel drivers are there in the system,
系统中有哪些内核驱动
like in the dev slash dev kernel devices
比如 /dev/ 下的内核设备
and then which ones of those are accessible from a normal user
然后哪些驱动是普通用户可以访问的
and not just root.
而不仅仅是 root 用户
And then I went in
然后我就开始行动了
and started looking at that code and auditing that way.
开始查看这些代码并进行审计
How much reversing is required?
需要多少逆向工程？
Do you guys love reversing?
你们喜欢逆向工程吗？
Are there any reverser heads here?
这里有没有逆向工程的高手？
Yeah?
是吗？
You should just leave.
你还是走吧
No, just kidding.
不 开玩笑的
But you have to think about that, right?
但你得考虑一下 对吧？
It's like, do you want to be
比如 你想要
Because if you're finding a bug in a closed source kernel driver
因为如果你要在闭源内核驱动中发现漏洞
you have to spend a ton of time reversing that kernel driver
你得花很多时间去逆向那个内核驱动程序
to understand how it works, what the data structures are
弄清楚它是怎么工作的,有什么数据结构
to even then start to find bugs
然后才能开始找漏洞
and then what to do with it.
然后再想怎么利用它
So think about that.
所以想想这个问题
This is actually, the ironic thing is I started
其实 讽刺的是 我一开始
because before I'd actually thought about targeting
并没有考虑过攻击目标
I was just like, yeah, Whatever
我只是无所谓
I like Apple products.
我喜欢苹果的产品
As you can see
正如你所见
I have like already three on this table right here
我在这张桌上已经有三个了
and two more in this bag and one on my wrist.
袋子里还有两个 手腕上有一个
Is there any more?
还有更多吗？
And I was like,
然后我心想
yeah, it'd be fun to do.
嗯 做这个挺好玩的
And I want to get better at reversing
我想提高逆向工程的技能
because I don't really like reversing
因为我不太喜欢逆向工程
but I want to get better at reversing.
但我还是想提高逆向工程的技能
And so I want to go through those kernel modules and do all this stuff.
所以我打算研究这些内核模块 做这些事情
And then when I started looking at it
当我开始研究时
I found out actually the kernel is open source
我发现内核原来是开源的
and the source code is there.
源代码就在这儿
And guess what?
猜猜怎么着
If I want to spend my time
如果我有时间
I want to spend my time finding bugs, not reversing code.
我想把时间花在找 bug 上 而不是逆向分析代码
And I can read the kernel source code.
而且我能读内核源代码
It's amazing.
那太棒了
And you can even compare it side by side in your editor and your IDA
你可以把代码编辑器和IDA放在一起，比较
so you can match it up directly
可以直接对比
and make reversing so much easier.
让逆向分析更轻松
Yeah, so think about that depending on what you want to do it.
所以 根据你的目标好好想想
Okay.
好吧
Leading to the next point.
接下来是下一个要点
Why are you doing this?
你为什么要做这个？
Right?
对吧？
You should understand your own
你应该了解自己
I know this I don't know
我知道这，
maybe sounds weird or metaphysical or something, but like
可能听起来有点奇怪或玄乎 但就是说
why do you want to do this and find bugs?
你为什么想做这个并找到漏洞？
This probably should have been the first slide
这本来应该是第一个幻灯片
but do you just want to make money?
但你只是想赚钱吗？
Yeah, you can do it.
当然可以
You may want to have fun.
你可能想图个乐子
You may want to learn.
你可能想学点东西
You may want to do a combination of those things.
你可能想兼顾以上几方面
So yeah, what's your goal doing all this?
所以 你做这些的目的是什么？
How much time and effort do you have?
你有多少时间和精力？
Is this going to be just a weekend thing
这会只是周末做的事情吗
that you're doing while you're in school?
你上学时会做吗
So maybe you'll take one or two days a week,
所以你可能会每周抽出一两天
do some vulnerability analysis.
来做漏洞分析
If that is your plan
如果这是你的计划
I would then use that to select a target correctly that...
接下来我会用它来选择合适的目标...
And make sure,
确保
because if you've ever tried to reverse something like one day a week
因为如果你尝试过每周花一天时间做逆向
it can be a massive pain
这会非常头疼
because you forget everything from your last reversing session.
因为你可能会忘了上次逆向的内容
That stuff really builds on each other.
这些内容是互相累积的
So if you don't have enough time
所以如果你时间不够
if it's something that's easier to reverse
如果是比较容易逆向的
or you can set up a fuzzer
或者你可以设置一个模糊器
and just let it run
让它运行
and then check it once a week
每周检查一次
that would be kind of a good strategy there.
这确实是个不错的方法
But you can think about your time and effort
但也可以考虑你的时间和精力
and how that impacts things.
以及这些的影响
And again, what do you know?
再说 你了解什么？
What is something that you know, right?
你了解什么 对吧？
What are your strengths?
你的优势是什么？
Play to your strengths.
发挥你的优势
I've been saying fuzzing is great over and over again.
我反复说 模糊测试非常棒
Maybe you don't know anything about fuzzing.
也许你对模糊测试不太了解
Maybe you're a code QL expert or a static analysis expert.
也许你是代码查询或静态分析的专家
Like those are actually totally fine.
这些都挺好
But like, yeah, play to those things.
不过 利用好这些长处
Okay.
好的
How are we doing on time?
我们时间怎么样？
How long does this class actually go to?
这堂课要上多久？
Okay, wow.
好 哇
I guess I got to go faster.
看来我得加快进度了
Let's do some more stuff.
我们再做点其他的事情
Anyways, selecting things.
话说 选择工具
These are things that you should absolutely be thinking about all the time.
这些是你应该时刻考虑的
Can you build it?
你能构建出来吗？
Can you run it?
你能运行吗？
Can you debug it?
你能调试吗？
Can you modify it?
你能修改吗？
Right?
对吧？
Oftentimes I, well, I won't blow up anyone's secret information
通常 嗯 我不会泄露别人的秘密信息
but I know people that even though they had access to systems
但我认识一些人 他们虽然有权限访问系统
and access to debug things
和调试权限
because they were able to build a complex target
但因为他们能编译构建复杂的系统
they just added print statements and did print statement debugging.
他们只是加了些打印语句来调试
And for them, that was way easier than learning how to debug a target.
对他们来说 这比学习调试目标容易多了
But they had access that not many of us can have.
但他们有我们多数人没有的权限
And so you have to do things the hard way.
所以你只能用更艰难的方法
So yeah, thinking about this kind of thing
所以 考虑这种问题很重要
this is like really important to figure out
这一点真的很重要 需要弄清楚
because if you don't have a good setup here
因为如果没有好的装备
you will drive yourself crazy
你会把自己逼疯
and you'll know that you're not being as efficient as possible
你会发现自己效率不高
and like wasted time is the worst time.
浪费时间最糟糕
Then you need to ask yourself
那你得问自己
how can I attack this target, right?
我该怎么对付这个目标 对吧？
This is the key thing
这是关键
and this is where like starting from a high level, right?
这就像是从大局考虑 对吧？
And thinking about, okay
然后想一想
what are all the different ways that input gets into this system, right?
有多少种不同的方式可以输入到这个系统 对吧？
The better you think about this
对于这个，你思考的越好
you can think about things that other people aren't thinking about, right?
你就能想到别人想不到的东西 对吧？
So, you know, I was saying text messages on here, right?
刚刚我说了，对于这个iphone，可以发短信
I think Android also had a problem.
我觉得 Android 也有这个问题
This was, I think, StageFrame
这大概是在StageFrame中
where they would generate automatically thumbnails of any movie or image,
他们会自动生成任何电影或图片的缩略图
maybe image, but anyways
也许是图片，但总之
I think the bug was in an audio or video library.
我觉得这个漏洞出在音频或视频库中
Anyways.
总之
They were generating thumbnails
他们在生成缩略图
even if you didn't even look at the text message
即使你没查看短信
of any message that was sent to you.
发送给你的任何消息内容
And there was a bug in that image parsing library
而那个图像解析库有一个漏洞
that allowed somebody to pop out.
可以让攻击者得逞
And so they could send you one text message and boom
所以他们可以给你发一条短信 然后
your whole phone is compromised from there.
你的整个手机就被攻破了
So like thinking, like understanding that the system does that, right,
理解系统是如何工作的 对吧
is like a key part of understanding that attack surface.
这是理解那次攻击的关键
Where are things coming from?
这些数据是从哪里来的？
Where does the system get input?
系统从哪里获取输入？
where does input go in
这个输入会到哪里去
where does the output go
输出去哪里了？
right what things does this talk to it sounds trivial
这东西和什么通信？听起来简单
but in a complex system it's like it can get crazy
但在复杂的系统中 情况会变得很复杂
um other things this is why part of the reason
这也是为什么我们
we talk about things at the lower division security levels
我们在较低的安全级别上讨论这些问题
what's the access control model like
访问控制模型是怎样的？
who can do what
谁有权限做什么？
and what are the privilege levels
权限层级又是怎样的？
Modern systems are absolutely crazy in all the different privilege levels they have
现代系统的权限层级简直太复杂了
right?
对吧？
A lot of things will pay out for privilege escalation
很多情况下 提升权限都能带来收益
and it doesn't have to be a use after free that leads to a yada, yada.
不一定是因为UAF 导致的一系列
It could be a logic bug
可能是逻辑漏洞
that allowed you to do something you weren't supposed to do
导致你做了不该做的事情
and you can get paid by that stuff.
这些漏洞也能带来收入
Like a key thing that's absolutely crazy to me is
比如 有一件事情我觉得特别不可思议
this is from research stuff, not bug bounties,
这是研究成果 不是漏洞赏金
but like WordPress, anybody know WordPress?
但说到 WordPress 有人知道吗？
Is it an important piece of software?
这算是一款重要的软件吗？
No?
不是吗？
Yeah.
对
You all think PHP is like so boomer technology that, yeah.
大家都觉得 PHP 是老掉牙的技术 对吧
It's still like one of the most deployed
但它仍然是部署最广泛的
and run pieces of software on earth.
在地球上运行的软件之一
It's like insane.
简直不可思议
WordPress runs so many sites.
WordPress 支撑着这么多网站
And so you can have a cross-site scripting in like WordPress.
WordPress 中也可能出现XSS
And a lot of times you'll think it's, oh
很多时候你可能会觉得 哎
it's just a self XSS.
这只是一个自我 XSS 问题
Like it's an admin.
比如 只是一个管理员
And on the admin panel
在管理员面板上
it's a cross-site scripting.
是一个XSS
But it turns out in WordPress
但在 WordPress 中
there are super admins.
有超级管理员
because you can have a WordPress install
你安装 WordPress后
where you have a bunch of different separate WordPresses
其中有多个独立的 WordPress 实例
and each of them are admins
每个都是管理员
so you could actually elevate up one more privilege level.
你可以提升到更高的权限
I didn't understand this until I was doing research with some people
直到和一些人研究这个时 我才明白这一点
and we found these self-XSSs
我们发现了这些自我 XSS
and we're like
我们当时就想
what actually is a self-XSS?
到底什么是自我 XSS？
And you realize these permission models are just absolute bonkers.
你才会意识到这些权限模型简直疯了
So if you can understand that
所以 如果你能理解到
to the level that you can make it do something
足以让它做些
it's not supposed to do
它本来不会做的事情
then that's great and part of understanding the attack surface.
那太好了 这也是理解攻击面的一部分
Where's the data stored?
数据存储在哪里？
How can you mess with data?
你怎样修改数据？
What things you can change?
你能改什么？
Those are all basic kind of stuff.
这些都是基础的东西
Okay.
好的
And what does the system depend on, right?
系统依赖什么？
The dependencies.
依赖项
Okay.
好的
Another key thing, and I'm going to show an example here.
还有一件重要的事 我来举个例子
This is the example I was talking about earlier.
就是我前面提到的要讲的例子
So you can spend
你可以花时间
this is not a CTF.
这不是 CTF
You need to get that into your heads
你们得领会这一点
when you are doing vulnerability analysis of a real target.
在分析真实目标的漏洞时
It is not a CTF.
这不是 CTF
Nobody planted a fun little vulnerability
没有人特意种下小漏洞
that you're just going to look at some code
让你从代码里找到
and find it immediately and be like, oh, this is great.
然后马上找到 说 哦 太棒了
I love this.
我喜欢这样
This is like, there may not be any exploitable bugs.
这里可能根本就没有可利用的漏洞
There may be plenty of bugs.
可能会有很多漏洞
They may not be exploitable.
但未必能利用
So you can spend a ton of time on one component and find nothing.
你可能花大把时间在一个组件上 却一无所获
Or you can find bugs that aren't triggerable.
或者你发现的漏洞根本触发不了
You can, this is like, yeah, this is crazy.
你可能会觉得 这太疯狂了
I think a good strategy is to try to cast a wide net
我认为一个好的策略是广泛撒网
as wide as you can.
尽可能广泛
Look for easy, dumb vulnerabilities
查找那些容易发现的低级漏洞
in like in a very shallow manner possible.
尽量浅显地
See what you can find and then explore those more.
看看你能找到什么 再进一步深入
And then you can go deep as you get more experience in things.
随着你对事物越来越熟悉 再深入挖掘
I think specifically the example here
我认为这里有一个具体的例子
I'll show you the guys this.
我给你们展示一下
I think there's a similar example Basically
我认为有个类似的例子
this is what I was mentioning.
这就是我提到的
It wasn't until the end of my XNU journey that I realized
直到我的 XNU 之旅结束 我才意识到
I should be targeting important things
我应该关注重要的内容
that are in the kernel that user space a normal user could talk to.
普通用户可以交互的内核部分
It turns out, anybody know SMB, Samba, what that is?
结果 有人知道 SMB 或 Samba 是什么吗？
Yeah, what is it?
嗯 那是什么？
No, no, back there.
不 不 后面那位
Yeah, way to remotely access files exported by one system to another.
嗯 这是一种系统之间远程访问文件的方式
I think it's NFS, right, underneath
我认为底层是 NFS 对吧？
and that's protocol is?
那个协议是？
That's a different one?
那是个不同的吗？
Okay.
好的
Thank you, random person who nobody in the room knows.
谢谢你 这个房间里谁都不认识的人
So I started looking in that right at the end of my sabbatical, and...
所以我在休学术假的末尾开始研究这个
Yeah, so this is, don't get too excited.
对 别太激动
This is a version
这是一个版本
so I was looking at, I think
所以我觉得我在研究
because I started this
因为我开始研究这个
I think I was looking at a version of XNU from like 2021, 2022.
我觉得我在研究 2021 年或 2022 年的 XNU 版本
Anyways, at the start of my sabbatical
总之 在我休假开始的时候
it was towards the end
已经接近尾声了
like nine months later
大概九个月后
and I set the fuzzer up
我设置了一个模糊测试器
I harnessed the SMB client or the SMB stuff,
利用了 SMB 客户端或者其他 SMB 相关的东西
And then it, boom
结果 砰的一声
it popped out bugs literally immediately.
结果立刻就找到了漏洞
And they were the stupidest, like
那些漏洞蠢得不行 比如说
copy the struct sent from the user has a length field
用户发送的结构体有一个长度字段
that was never checked.
从未被检查过
And it's just copied right into kernel memory.
结果直接被复制到了内核内存中
And I was like, oh
我心想 哦
I'm so smart.
我真是太聪明了
I am absolutely getting paid.
我肯定能拿到钱了
Then I tried to run it.
然后我试着运行了
My POC on the test laptop that I had couldn't trigger it.
我测试笔记本上的概念验证代码，触发不了这个漏洞
And then I realized that somebody had already found those bugs.
后来我才发现已经有人找到这些漏洞了
before I had ever looked at that.
在我研究之前
But in that time, like in the six months
但在那段时间 比如过去的六个月里
like when I'd started my sabbatical
比如在我开始休假时
I think like three months before I started looking at it
大概在我开始研究之前三个月
they had already fixed those bugs.
他们已经修复了那些问题
So anyways, I wanted to show this.
所以 我想展示一下这个
I think it was something like this
大概就是这样
of just like this put_mem.
就像这个put_mem
So like put memory in here from this CP with this segment length
就像这里的put_mem, 从cp, seglen长度
where the segment link was never checked
这个seglen从未被检查过
and just like copied in somewhere exactly like this.
就直接复制到了某个地方 完全就是这样
I wanted to find the exact thing
我想找到具体的东西
but I couldn't.
但我找不到了
I got a little distracted, but.
我有点分心了
It was something like this.
大致如此
Anyways, so it's, there are
总之 就是这样
if I had just probably taken the time
如果我当时花点时间
of understanding what are all the system calls that a user could access
了解用户可以访问的所有系统调用
and then just looking at them, like one or two functions deep,
然后查看这些调用 大概一两层函数深
like not even very deep
其实也不算深
of like, okay, this user input
比如 这个用户输入
does it have a length field?
它有没有长度字段？
Is the input weird in this struct?
这个结构体里的输入是否异常？
Let's look at where that's used.
我们看看它在哪里被使用
Let's look at where that's copied around.
我们再看看它在哪些地方被复制
Oh crap, there's a bug.
糟了 有个 bug
Like I could have found stuff like way, way, way faster.
我本可以快得多找到这些问题
than if I just got super deep into several things
而不是深陷于几件事里
and tried a lot of stuff.
试了很多方法
So anyways, learn from my experience.
所以 总之 吸取我的教训
Okay.
好的
Yeah, there we go.
对 就是这样
Final two things.
最后两件事
So this is kind of a double-edged sword.
所以这就像一把双刃剑
I don't know.
我不知道
And maybe I'm just full of it, but...
也许我只是在瞎说 但...
We talked about reverse engineering.
我们讨论过逆向工程了
Remember, reverse engineering does not just mean understanding a binary,
记住 逆向工程不只是理解二进制
right?
对吧？
Reverse engineering is understanding a system.
逆向工程是理解系统
If that system is only in binary form
如果系统只有二进制形式
you need to understand that binary.
你就需要理解这个二进制
So even if you have the source code
即使你有源代码
you need to understand the components
你也需要理解这些组件
and how they all work together.
以及它们是如何协同工作的
As you'll see later in the class
你们在接下来的课程中会看到
we'll get into like, I mean
我们详细讲一下 我是说
we saw it there in that XNU code.
我们在那个 XNU 代码里见过
You can like kind of see what's going on there
你可以大概看出来那里发生了什么
but it's not very clear.
但不是很清楚
And there's these MBs
还有一些 MBs
which are some buffers
是一些缓冲区
and there are special data structure that's only, I think
还有一种特殊的数据结构 我认为
I think it's used in network communication in the kernel.
它主要用在内核的网络通信中
I'm not sure.
我不确定
I can't remember if that was a specific thing to that kernel module or not
我不记得那是不是那个内核模块独有的
but you have to understand things
但你必须了解情况
but you have to remember this is not a CTF.
但你要记住 这不是夺旗赛
In a CTF, oftentimes
在夺旗赛中 通常
your reverse engineering goal is to understand every single bit and byte in that thing
你的逆向工程目标是理解每一个比特以及每一个字节
and to get this beautiful I to decompilation
并能得到这么漂亮的 IDA 反编译结果
where everything looks great because you know every single structure
一切看起来都很棒 因为你了解每一个结构
and every single field and everything.
以及每一个字段和所有细节
That is not the goal.
这不是目标
There is no end state here.
这里没有终点
You could do that and not find anything.
你这样做也可能什么都找不到
And then guess what?
你猜怎么着？
They'll release a new version in three months
他们将在三个月后发布一个新版本
that completely changed the stuff
这个版本将完全改变现有的内容
and you'll have to redo it.
你得重新来过
And then three months later, things will change.
然后三个月后 情况又会变
This literally happened to me
这真的发生在我身上
when I was trying to POC I was trying to create an exploit from a POC I had
我试图用我的 POC 来创建一个漏洞利用程序时
which was a heap underwrite.
它是一个堆下溢
So it was writing a pointer like one byte beyond a thing.
所以它在对象之外的一个字节处写入了一个指针
So I was trying to do all this heap grooming
所以我尝试进行堆规整
and everything to get exact thing that I could control.
为了能完全控制每一个细节
And anyways, I was almost doing it.
反正 我几乎就要搞定了
I was very, very close.
我就差那么一点点
And then I upgraded to the next version
然后我升级到了下一个版本
which was a point release.
那只是一个小版本更新
It was like 11.3 instead of 11.2.
从 11.2 更新到了 11.3
And they completely changed the way the allocator worked in the kernel.
他们彻底改写了内核中分配器的机制
And they randomized it much more.
并且使随机性大大增加
And then my beautifully crafted heap manipulation was like completely dead.
然后我精心设计的堆操作变得毫无用处
And I was like I just need to submit this.
我就剩提交了
I spent like a month trying to do this thing it driving myself crazy.
我花了近一个月尝试做这件事 几乎要疯了
But this is not to say you don't need to know things.
但这并不意味着你不需要了解相关知识
I think that's the flip side of the coin.
我觉得这是另一面
So I think one side of the coin is don't go too deep and too focused on things.
所以我觉得 不要过于深入和专注
You still need to remember
你还是要记住
that you're trying to eventually find stuff.
你最终是要找到东西的
Be cognizant of getting stuck when you're just spinning your wheels, right?
原地打转时 要意识到可能卡住了
And doing too much time reversing.
还有 不要花太多时间逆向
But keep notes.
但要做好记录
I almost never take notes on anything.
我几乎从不记笔记
That was an absolute mistake
那绝对是个错误
when I started doing this stuff.
我刚开始做这些事
Like you having to re-reverse engineer what the bug is
你得重新分析这个 Bug
and why it works and why the POC works or...
以及它为什么能工作 POC 为什么有效
this allocator stuff
这些内存分配器的问题
because I was I don't know traveling or doing something.
当初我在旅行，还是忙其他事
But like, I went like a week later to look at the thing
但是 一周后 我再去查看这些东西
and I was like, oh no, I like reversed, you know
天哪，我大概逆向了
five levels of this allocator and how it was working.
这个分配器的五个层级和它的工作原理
And I had to do all of that again to re-understand what was going on
我不得不重新做一遍 才能理解到底发生了什么
because I didn't take any notes.
因为我没有做笔记
And that's why I was like, okay, this time, writing a text
所以我这次下定决心 要写点东西
just whatever makes sense to you, the easiest, writing a text field,
随便写点对你有帮助的东西 用最简单的方式
like just please take notes.
拜托 一定要做笔记
Like this stuff is complex.
这些东西真的很复杂
It's not something you can always just keep in your head.
这些不是你能一直记在脑子里的东西
Because this was the crazy thing
因为这真是太疯狂了
and this is a story I wanted to share
这是我想要分享的一个故事
is that you never actually know
你永远不知道
when something is going to be useful.
什么时候某件事会派上用场
Like, you may understand a feature
比如说 你可能理解了一个功能
and it may actually cause a bug to be triggerable that wasn't triggerable.
这可能引发一个原本不能触发的 bug
So this was a bug I found to prepare for my sabbatical
所以 这是我在准备休假时发现的一个 bug
Wait, no, don't do that.
等一下 别这么做
Ah, don't do that, for sure.
啊 千万别这么做
What are you doing?
你在干什么？
Okay.
好的
Anyways...
总之...
okay before my sabbatical I wanted to like prepare and practice
在我休假前 我打算练练手
and I guess limbered up or whatever
热热身之类的
and to do that I tried to do pwn2own with somebody else
我试着和别人一起做个 pwn2own
targeting the Tesla so
目标是特斯拉 结果
we like I did the exact mistake I was warning you against.
我犯了之前警告过你们的错误
I went super deep
我研究得很深入
and I like found a feature that
我发现了一个功能
it's this feature where you can plug in a USB drive to get an audio thing to play.
你可以插入 U 盘播放音频
And the car doors open in sequence to that.
车门会随着音频依次打开
I can't remember what the feature is called.
我记不起这功能叫什么了
I was like, oh
我当时心想 哇
it's a super cool vector.
这是个超酷的攻击向量
Like think about just like plug the USB drive in and like boom
想象一下 插上 U 盘 就能搞定
you've popped the system.
你就搞定了系统
And I started digging in
然后我开始研究
I figured out the exact library they were using for this audio player
我查到了他们用的音频播放器的库
which was this GStreamer
就是 GStreamer
which is an open source audio playing system.
这是一个开源的音频播放系统
They also didn't do any checks that the MP3 file was actually MP3
他们也没有检查文件是否真的是 MP3
so the intact service was any of the installed plugins and libraries.
所以任何已安装的插件和库都能使用
So actually I used ？？ to find, I think
实际上我用 ？？ 发现了一些潜在的问题 我觉得
one potential bug that wasn't actually useful
一个潜在的 bug 但没实际用处
but I did end up patching in here.
但我还是在这里打了个补丁
So I used some static analysis tools
所以我用了一些静态分析工具
but honestly it was a lot of reading code
但说实话 这涉及到大量的代码阅读
and just like I would grep through all this stuff for malloc
我会用 grep 查找所有这些 malloc 的用法
or gmalloc because it was actually a different allocator,
或者是 gmalloc 因为那实际上是另一种内存管理器
but for gmalloc to find every single use
但为了找到每一个使用 gmalloc 的地方
and just like read the code a few lines back
然后往前看几行代码
and you can see super weird stuff like integer overflows,
你就能看到像整数溢出这样的奇怪问题
all this kind of stuff.
等等
Anyways, to I guess spoil it
话说回来 我要剧透一下
I was never able to land this
我始终没能成功利用
and I drove myself crazy trying to land this because it was a
我为此快把自己逼疯了 因为这实际上是个
actually you can see here, so
实际上 你可以看到
The vulnerability was an integer overflow here.
这里的漏洞是整数溢出
So there's this MKV is Matroska.
所以 MKV 就是 Matroska 格式
And this, basically there was this thing.
这，就是这个
So this blocksize.
这个blocksize
So if blocksize was very large
如果blocksize非常大
adding this constant value to it would cause it to be small.
加上这个常量后 它就会变得很小
And so it would allocate a small buffer.
于是它会分配一个小缓冲区
And then later on
然后稍后
it would copy block size from data to out data, right?
它会从data拷贝blocksize大小的数据到outdata中 对吧？
Classic integer overflow.
典型的整数溢出
I believe...
我认为……
Yeah, this is all in one function.
是的 这都在一个函数里
So this like is very clear
所以这非常明显
when you're looking at the code that this is a bug.
查看代码时 这是一个 bug
And so you get super stoked.
于是你非常兴奋
You're like, ah, yes
你就像 啊 好
I'm a genius.
我简直是个天才
I found this bug.
我发现了一个bug
I'm going to get so much money.
我要大赚一笔
I wanna a Tesla.
我要买一个tesla
This is going to be awesome.
这太棒了
And this is not like hyperbole.
我可不是在夸张
This is like actually what I was stupidly thinking at the time.
这真的是我当时很傻的想法
Anyways.
不管怎样
And then you create this MKV file.
然后你创建了这个 MKV 文件
So you find out the MKV format
于是你了解了 MKV 格式
you create an MKV file that does exactly this thing.
你创建了一个能实现这个功能的 MKV 文件
And then you do it and it doesn't work.
然后你这么做了 但它不起作用
And you're like why doesn't it work?
你心想 为什么不起作用？
This is insane.
这太离谱了
There's a classic integer overflow right here.
这里有一个典型的整数溢出
Well, you realize that actually there's a size check.
你发现其实有一个大小检查
So there's a size check in this other function.
这个大小检查在另一个函数中
So again, this is why this stuff can be very complex,
所以 这就是为什么这些事情非常复杂
especially with static analysis.
尤其是静态分析时
You can look at one function or several functions
你可以查看一个函数或几个函数
see that there's a bug
发现了一个 bug
but not realize that's 15 functions deep
但没意识到这个 bug 隐藏得很深 涉及到 15 个函数
or that data that you're using was checked
或者你输入的数据实际上检查过
in an earlier part of the code you haven't even looked at
在你还没看的前面的代码中
for size or something like that.
比如对size或类似数据的校验
So there's a size check
所以有大小检查
which checks max block size
这个会检查最大块的大小
which I believe was
我相信这个大小
I don't know.
我不太确定
I can't remember the size.
我不记得大小了
I think it was 15 megs or something
我觉得大概是 15 兆
which is not enough because I guess I don't have it here.
这不够 因为我这儿没有写
But this block size
但这个blocksize
I think was an int, so a 32-bit number.
我觉得是 32 位的整型
I think that's right
我觉得没错
because it was like a four gig overwrite.
因为它好像是 4GB 的覆盖
Yeah, that's the only thing that makes sense.
对 这是唯一的解释
Anyways, so to do this
总之 要实现这一点
because this was a fixed thing
因为这是个固定的量
you would have had to create a block size that was almost four gigs, right?
你得创建一个接近 4GB 的块 对吧？
And then added a little bit more
然后再稍微加一点
that would create a small buffer
这样可以创建一个小缓冲区
that you could overwrite with your huge buffer.
你可以用大缓冲区覆盖它
But this max block size stopped that.
但最大块大小限制了这一点
So it only allowed your block size to be 15 megs.
所以它只允许块大小为 15 兆
And so I was super disappointed.
所以我非常失望
And then like a day or two later
然后一两天后
it dawned on me while I was reading this code
我在读这段代码时突然意识到
that there was a feature in these blocks that had compression so
这些块有一个压缩功能
that you could decompress the block size.
你可以解压缩块大小
And that happened after the size check, but before this copy.
这发生在大小检查之后 但在复制之前
And so what I was able to do was it was Zlib
我能用的是 Zlib
and there was three different compression mechanisms.
有三种不同的压缩机制
I had to test all of them to see
我必须测试每一种
which one would actually let you create a resulting file
看哪种能生成我需要的
that was the size I needed of four gigs of memory.
4GB 的文件
And it was actually able to do that.
竟然真的能行
So using those two
所以利用这两种方法
like using the knowledge I'd learned just from reading the code
利用我从代码中学到的知识
and kind of doing that reverse engineering process was like
以及逆向工程的过程
I would not have been able to trigger that bug without this thing.
没有这个过程 我根本无法触发这个漏洞
So.
所以
Anyways, but landing this was almost insane.
不过 搞定这事儿简直疯了
I still have nightmares of trying to do this
我做梦都在尝试这事儿
because it's an audio file
因为这是音频文件
so you have one shot, right?
你只有一次机会 对吧？
And so I arranged the heap
所以我安排了堆内存
so I could survive the four gig write by making other tracks
通过创建其他音轨来完成 4GB 的写入
and everything that get allocated and massaging the heap.
和其它分配堆内存的操作 调整堆内存
You could survive that four gig write
你才能撑过那 4GB 的写入
and then you're like, great, I did that.
然后你心想 太好了 我做到了
What do I write?
我该写些什么？
Then you start looking.
然后你开始找
What are all the structs I can allocate?
我能分配哪些结构体？
Great, there's a function pointer.
太好了 有个函数指针
Ah, but there's ASLR
啊 但有 ASLR
so I can't just arbitrarily do anything.
所以我不能随心所欲
What are the targets I can go to?
我可以攻击哪些目标？
And I tried a bunch of things
我试了很多
couldn't find anything
但没找到
and I had to stop
我不得不停下来
because I was doing this on weekends
因为是在周末做的
and hating my life on those weekends
搞得我哪些周末都自闭了
because I was just getting stuck on this
因为我在这上面卡住了
because I'd gone down so far in this rabbit hole
因为我已经深陷这个兔子洞里了
of this was the only way I was going to do this
这是我唯一的办法
and it was just horrible.
简直太糟糕了
So anyways, learn from that.
所以 大家吸取教训吧
Okay, questions?
好了 有什么问题吗？
Okay.
好的
Do you guys think you can hack stuff now?
你们觉得现在能黑进东西了？
Hmm?
嗯？
That's mean.
这太刻薄了
Not here to offend himself.
不是来惹自己的
Ah, what's going on?
啊 怎么回事？
Okay.
好的
Well, let's see how elite you are.
好吧 看看你有多厉害
We'll do like 20 minutes of this.
我们来做 20 分钟吧
Okay.
好的
Where was that stupid thing?
那愚蠢的东西在哪？
Exploit me？
Okay.
好的
So now we are in.
现在我们进来了
Oh, and then the silly thing was
哦 结果呢 那事儿还挺逗的
so I spent all this effort on this stuff
我在这上面花了好多功夫
and I thankfully had read that Google has a patch,
好在我看到 Google 有个
a vulnerability patch program.
漏洞修补项目
where they will pay you for patching vulnerabilities
他们会为修补漏洞支付报酬
that exist in important open source software.
那些存在于重要的开源软件中的漏洞
And what they define as open source
他们对开源软件的定义是
is anything that's been harnessed with OSS fuzz.
就是用 OSS Fuzz 处理过的软件
And this stuff was harnessed with OSS fuzz.
这些东西就是用 OSS Fuzz 处理过的
So I was actually able to then get
所以我最后得了
I got like $500 from this.
我从这赚了 500 美元
So at least I got something out of like three months of effort
至少这三个月的努力 我还是有点收获的
besides purely failure.
不算完全失败
But I know it's cool.
但我还是觉得这很酷
I got like a bunch of bugs fixed.
我修复了一堆 bug
So that part was fun.
这部分还挺有趣的
But yeah, it was crazy.
但确实有点疯狂
Here's our program.
这是我们的程序
Have you guys ever group hacked before?
你们以前有组队开黑过吗？
So we have this program, exploit 64.
我们有这个叫 exploit 64 的程序
There's level one is hello as the password, hello and pass in a value.
第一关的密码是'hello' 输入'hello'并传递一个值
Value less or equals zero is not allowed.
不允许小于或等于零
So what do we do next?
那我们接下来该怎么办？
And I can just use ObjDump
我可以用 ObjDump 来分析
because this is actually the one nice thing about using an Apple Silicon Mac
因为这是使用苹果硅芯片 的一大优势
is because it's running ARM with UTM
因为用 UTM 运行的 ARM
or whatever that I'm using in Apple's virtualization stuff.
还是什么苹果的虚拟化技术
I can run a native Linux VM locally on my thing
我可以在我的设备上本地运行一个 Linux 虚拟机
and then all the tools work when it works and so.
这样一切正常时 所有工具都能正常工作
That part's kind of nice, but ...
这部分还挺不错的 但是……
Okay.
好的
Oh, God.
天哪
It's ...
是……这个
Oh, no.
糟了
Does this mean it's ...
这意味着……
Whatchamacallit?
那个什么来着？
Yes.
是
Yeah.
嗯
It's C++.
是 C++
I'm regretting this immediately.
我立刻就后悔了
Okay.
行
Also, we just crashed objdump.
另外 刚刚把objdump搞崩了
Is that a failure?
这是失败了吗？
I feel like that shouldn't happen in objdump.
我感觉应该不是objdump出问题
Oh, good.
哦 还好
Okay, see, it's so resilient.
好的 它健壮性还挺好的
Okay, let's grab for level one.
好的 我们先查找一下level1
Okay, then we just open it up in IDA
好吧 我们用IDA看一下
because we tried this and said, yep.
这个没弄好
Okay.
好的
13?
13？
Oh, level 13.
哦 第 13 关
Yeah, so this is a multi-level binary challenge in one binary, basically
这是一个多关卡的二进制挑战 都在一个文件里
so it's I don't know.
我也不太清楚
I just saw it on GitHub.
我在 GitHub 上看到的
I have the link somewhere in here.
链接就在这儿的某个地方
So if you want to try it out, you can.
所以如果你想试试 就尽管来吧
All right.
好的
Source.
源码
Exploit me.
来黑我吧
I know you all saw that.
我知道你们都看到了
Source directory, but we're not gonna do it.
源代码目录 但我们先不这样做
All right, should we start at the start?
好的 要从start开始吗？
At main?
从main开始？
Can you all read this?
大家都能看清吗？
Or do you need me to zoom in somehow?
或者需要我放大一些？
Back row, yeah?
后排 看清了吗？
Okay.
好的
Oh, somebody said, why do I look like Tom Cruise?
哦 有人问为什么我长得像汤姆·克鲁斯？
Well, I don't know.
这个我也说不准
All right, okay.
好的 就这样
Looks like we have all the passwords here.
看来我们这里有所有的密码了
Hello, help, velvet, my secret.
Pretty nice, we've already got passwords.
不错 我们已经拿到密码了
But we actually want to exploit it, right?
但我们其实是想漏洞利用 对吧？
We're not just here for the free passwords.
我们不是为了密码来的
Okay.
好的
So this is...
所以这就是...
Okay, so argv[1], I gotta assume...
好的 argv[1] 我猜猜看...
Sorry, sorry.
抱歉 抱歉
Oh, this is passwords, aHelp.
哦 这是密码 aHelp
Oh, I see.
哦 明白了
Okay.
好的
It's supposed to be a list
这里是列表
and then it's like hard coding the value there.
这里写死的值
Passwords, argc, get effective user ID.
密码、argc 获取有效用户 ID
Oh, a nice function called int overflow.
哦 有一个很好的函数叫 int overflow
That seems helpful.
这看起来很有用
Okay, so argv[2], so our second argument.
好的 argv[2] 就是第二个参数
So our first argument has to be the password.
第一个参数必须是密码
The second argument is there.
第二个参数在这里
int_overflow()
Okay, so what's it doing?
好的 它做什么？
Taking our input, atoi
接收我们的输入 转换成整数
turning it into a local int.
转换成本地整数
Value less than or equal zero is not allowed.
值不能小于或等于零
If _WORD.
Okay, so now it's, if not it.
好的 如果是其他情况
What was that?
这是什么？
Yeah, okay, let's,
好的 开始吧
oh, oh, oh, the word.
哦 哦 哦 这个词
I hate these stupid things.
我讨厌这些破玩意
Okay, let's go here.
好的 咱们去这儿
Well, let's...
嗯 我们……
Now I want to give names.
现在我要给它们取名字
in_int.
输入的整数
Okay, great.
好的 太好了
Okay.
好的
I see.
我知道了
Yeah.
嗯
Okay.
行
I want to look at the assembly.
我想看看汇编
So we can kind of clearly see by looking at this.
这里我们可以清楚地看到
So move, wait, store register, load register, store register.
所以 移动 等待 存储寄存器 加载寄存器 再存储寄存器
What's var_8?
var_8 是什么？
Why didn't this update?
为什么这里没更新？
No.
没有
Okay.
好的
Bunch of redundant stuff.
一堆多余的东西
Compare W0 with 0.
比较 W0 和 0
And then...
然后...
STRH, we looked at that last week, right?
STRH 我们上周讲过 对吧？
Yeah, so this is the, okay
嗯 所以这是 好的
,so it's still a 30, ah, okay.
所以还是 30 好的
So it's reading in a 32-bit, right
所以它读取的是 32 位 对吗？
which is the W0
就是 W0
and then the H here means half word
这里的 H 表示半字
which is two bytes.
就是两字节
Cool, so what number do we need?
酷 我们需要哪个数字？
Yeah, so OX.
对 所以是 0x
Actually, the thing I really like to do
其实我最喜欢做的事情是
there's this really handy-dandy bit thing here of doing like that.
这里有一个非常方便的位操作 就像这样
So you can just immediately set the bits.
所以你可以直接设置这些位
I mean, 10,000.
我的意思是 10000
Come on.
拜托了
I can't even say it's off by 10.
我甚至不能说它差了 10
Exactly.
没错
So that's the other.
这就是另一个
See, people are already thinking through.
你看 大家已经开始思考了
So the other question, right?
所以另一个问题 对吧？
So we think we know the bug.
所以我们认为已经找到这个 bug 了
The bug is?
这个 bug 是？
that this check is a 32-bit integer check
这是一个针对 32 位整数的检查
but this check is a 16, two-byte, wait
但这个检查是 16 位的 两个字节 等等
did I say 32?
我说的是 32 吗？
Yeah, 32 and 16-bit.
是的 32 位和 16 位
So if we can pass them
所以如果我们能通过这些检查
and this happens all the time
这种情况经常发生
and it is very helpful
这会非常有帮助
if you have like a multiply that causes an integer overflow
如果乘法导致整数溢出
you need to make sure that
你需要确保
those two numbers that you're giving are in the right proper thing.
这两个数字在正确的范围内
So making sure that
因此要确保
it's right within that range of like larger than this but smaller than this
它在大于这个，但小于这个值的范围内
So 10,000 hex
所以0x10,000
And yeah, so I will just do a quick man
我快速查看一下手册
because especially in honor of Rob since he's here
既然 Rob 在这里，我就借此向他致敬
we'll read the man page of atoi.
我们来阅读 atoi 的手册页
We will search through the man page.
我们在手册页中搜索一下
Ah, there we go.
啊 找到了
No, because the behavior is the same as strtol, null pointer 10.
因为它的行为和strtol(nptr, NULL, 10)一样
So string to long is
字符串转长整型
where you can specify the base.
你可以指定基数
So now our theory that we have developed as a group, what was it?
那么整体来看，推导出了什么呢
Hello.
你好
We pass in hello
我们传入“hello”
and we pass in 65536.
再传入 65536
Look at that.
看看
A whole bunch of hackers.
一堆黑客
How many people are in this room?
这个房间里有多少人？
Like 20 something?
大概 20 人？
Look at that.
你们看
Okay.
行
Help
I need somebody.
我需要个人
This is actually kind of fun.
这还挺有趣的
I don't know if you're having fun
我不知道你们觉得有趣吗
but the question is, do I care?
但我在乎吗？
Okay.
行
Attack overflow.
进行溢出攻击
Do we want to try to overflow things?
我们要不要试试溢出？
Like overflowing things?
就是溢出？
Okay.
好的
Username and password.
用户名和密码
Username, password.
用户名 密码
If. verify user, username is not equal to one, return zero.
如果用户名验证结果不等于 1 就返回 0
Okay, so there's some check. It's gonna check the input of username.
好的 这里有个检查，它会检查用户名
And again, this is where I like to not go too deep
这里正好对应前面说的不用看太深
and be like, oh yeah, well, what's that function?
不用像，哦，这个函数是干啥的？
What's that function?
那个函数是干啥的？
Verify user calls something else.
哦，verify_user 又调用了别的
It's like, you can just look at it as like, okay
就是，知道个轮廓就好
there's some check, obviously
显然有检查
because there's some if condition here.
因为这里有个 if 条件
Copy onto v4 funny,
先复制 funny 到 v4
then copy onto the second argument password onto v5.
再复制第二个参数 passwd 到 v5
And then, shouldn't this be a character pointer?
这应该是字符指针吧？
估计是rob问ida快捷键
I was just like, what you get asked in class
感觉像，课堂上别人问你的
and now you're reflecting it back on me?
现在你又把问题抛给我了？
Yeah.
嗯
it's like asking me what emacs shortcuts i do to do things
就像问我在 Emacs 上，用了哪些快捷键
it's like built in my brain  but yes i can
这些快捷键已经刻在脑子里了，但我可以
okay so um uh
嗯……
let's see n is to change variable names
我们看看 按 n 是用来更改变量名的
so you hit n you can change the variable name
所以你按 n 就可以更改变量名
hit y and you can change the type
按 y 更改变量类型
The thing that will drive me crazy is why people develop tools
让我抓狂的是 为什么这个工具
where you can change the type that has the name in it
改类型的时候，输入框里有名字
but if you change this name, nothing happens.
但如果你在这里改名字，不会生效
It's the most insane thing that anyone's ever developed this system
这是我见过最疯狂的系统
that shows you this.
它都展示了这个名字
They should be one thing.
他们应该是一回事
You can change the type and the name
你可以更改类型和名称
and it should just change.
它也应该随之改变
Anyways, okay.
总之 行吧
And then I think the only other ones I've been using...
另外 我觉得我常用的只有这些...
Oh, let's see
哦 看看...
function F5 to make it try to re-decompile.
Fn + F5 用于尝试重新反编译
Tab is the really important one to switch easily
Tab 键非常重要 可以轻松地
between decompilation view here and then the
往返于反编译视图与...
so like clicking on verify_user
比如说 点击verify_user
this means when I press tab
当我按下 Tab 键
it should be synced with that code here.
它应该和这里的代码同步
And so I should see a BL Z11verify_userPC.
所以 我应该看到 BL Z11verify_userPC.
Oh, it does demangle it. That's kind of cool.
哦 它确实解析了 这挺酷的
Is this a new thing?
这是新功能吗？
It always did it.
总是这样
Oh, okay.
哦 明白了
The free one.
免费版
Okay, funny over here.
好的 funny 这里
And then the other one is escape.
另一个是Esc
So escape goes backwards.
Esc会退回去
I don't know how to go forwards.
我不知道怎么前进
Is there a way for it? There must be, right?
有办法吗？肯定有办法吧？
Can you not go forward?
你不能前进吗？
What?
什么？
Are you defending Ida?
你是在给IDA辩护吗？
If you press escape and look in, like
你按Esc 看着 就像
There's two arrows.
有两个箭头
Jump to next position.
跳到下一个位置
Or, yeah.
嗯
Jump to next position.
跳到下个位置
Oh, wait.
等一下
Yeah, but what's the keyboard shortcut?
对 但快捷键是什么？
Anyways.
总之
Okay, so copy V4, funny V4 password.
好 复制funny到 V4，密码
Some strlen.
某种strlen函数
Why is it strlen_0?
为什么是strlen_0？
Is that like C++ stuff?
看着像C++代码
String length on zero.
将v5在v4长度位置的字节置0
What is this doing?
这是在做什么？
Probably checking the end of the string or something?
可能是检查字符串的结尾？
This must be a buffer, right?
这应该是缓冲区 对吧？
This is clearly a type.
这显然是个char数组
Yeah.
嗯
Right, okay.
好的 知道了
And then the other thing that's...
然后还有个……
Wait, but why?
等等 为什么？
Okay, first...
好的 首先...
Other thing we can do is the strcmp, right?
然后进行字符串比较 对吧？
So we have strcmp v4, v5.
会比较 v4 和 v5
we strcmp always takes two character pointers.
strcmp需要两个字符指针
So it's passing in the address of v5
所以它传入了 v5 的地址
which means v5 must be a buffer, right?
这意味着 v5 必须是一个缓冲区 对吧？
It's not a
它不是一个
so the type here is wrong.
所以这里自动识别的类型错了
It's saying that it's a 64 bit.
它说这是 64 位的
So it's what 64 bit would be character or the eight bytes.
所这个 64 位应该是char[8]
Is that right?
没错吧？
Yeah.
对
So that makes that look better.
这样一来就更好了
It makes this look worse, which is weird, but okay.
这让这个看起来更糟 虽然奇怪 但好吧
Oh, see, and then,
哦 你看 接下来
yeah, this is how you can tell that your decompilation is getting
是的 这就是反编译越来越准确的迹象
your reversing is better as the decompilation gets better.
反编译越准 逆向的也越好
So doing this, so calling strlen on v4
所以 对 v4 调用 strlen 函数
so however many characters v4 is
无论 v4 有多少字符
it's been nulling that byte of v5.
它都会把 v5 第v4长度的那个字节 置零
Is that right?
对吗？
So the string length is two.
所以字符串长度是 2
Yeah, 0, 1, 2
嗯 0, 1, 2
so that that way the resulting string is going to be the same length.
这样结果字符串的长度就会一致
Cool.
酷
Okay.
好的
And then if v4 is not funny, then...
然后如果 v5 不是funny 那么...
So the password, the idea is checking that it's funny.
所以就是检查passwd是不是funny
Why doesn't funny work?
为什么funny不行？
So just pass in funny and that work?
所只要输入funny就行吗
Oh, login succeeded, but you still failed.
哦 登录成功了， 但还是不行
Login failed.
登录失败
Let's go to verify user.
我们去验证一下用户
Okay, pressing N for username.
好的 按 N 输入用户名
It's not doing dictation.
不用语音输入
Okay, username.
好的 输入用户名
So similar thing, there's a V2, copy admin under there.
类似的，这里有个 V2，把admin拷贝到这里
Well, this is like the same thing.
嗯 基本完全一样
If only we had a way to like detect macros and common inline functions.
如果我们有一种方法能检测宏和常见的内联函数就好了
On V3, so I will go ahead and press Y
选中V3，然后按Y
to call this a
叫它
char
[8]
return one if it's not comparable to admin
如果不匹配admin 返回 1
and then login failed but
然后登录失败了 但是
where do you get the flag
你从哪里获取flag
oh yeah
哦 对了
that's funny so there's this nice uh function called stack overflow uh
挺有意思的 这个函数叫栈溢出
which should have been a hint i don't know why i wasn't thinking about that
这本该是个提示 不知道为什么我没想起来
but uh cool
不过 挺酷的
okay
好的
All right, should we overflow this?
好的 我们要让它溢出吗？
Yeah, maybe?
嗯 可以试试？
No, you don't want to?
不行 你不想？
Okay.
行
So we're strcopying into v3 here, the username.
所以我们把用户名复制到 v3
I guess we can technically choose whichever one we want.
我们技术上可以选任何一个
So let's help...
那我们help...
Let's see.
看看
So admin funny.
Login succeeded, but we still failed.
登录成功了 但还是失败了
Okay, so we do know the stuff that it wanted,
好的 我们清楚它需要什么
So if we did a bunch of A's, this is
所以如果输入一大串 A 会怎么样
I think this is
我觉得就是这样
you should all know this.
你们应该都懂这个
Bus error, core dumped, awesome.
总线错误 核心转储 真酷
Okay, so we exploited it.
好的 我们已经利用了
Now what do we wanna do?
现在该怎么办？
Or we haven't exploited it.
哦，我们还没利用它
We've proved that there's likely a vulnerability
我们已经证明这里很可能有漏洞
because we caused some weird stack behavior here.
因为我们这里引发了异常的栈行为
Wait, somebody says they didn't know tab syncs it.
等等 有人说不知道tab会同步？
Oh man, okay, I guess Rob was right.
哦 好吧 看来Rob说的对
I hate it when Rob's right.
我不喜欢Rob对的时候
Okay, so we are copying into
好的 我们在复制到
this is where I don't trust Ida, but okay
这里我不太信任 IDA 但就算了
this is our string copy.
这是我们的strcpy
So if we're using string copy
如果我们使用strcpy
what does that mean?
这意味着什么？
What was it?
什么？
Yeah, it doesn't, it implicitly checks.
对 它不直接 但会隐式检查
It means our payload can't have any null bytes
这意味着载荷不能包含空字节
which is a massive pain, right?
这真是个大麻烦 对吧？
So this is always, I think
所以 我认为
pwn college can do a lot of
pwn.college 做了很多
especially even in the challenges we're giving,
尤其是在我们提供的挑战中
a lot of hand-holding by using the read function
通过用read函数，降低了难度
which accepts any number of bytes.
它可以接受任意字节
And so it's really important on a real target to understand
所以 利用实际目标时，要明白这点
and take that next step and be like, okay
然后进行下一步时，要注意
but how is it reading in and what constraints is there, right?
它是如何读入数据的，有什么限制
Is it a scanf
它是用 scanf 吗？
which means no spaces and new lines and other things?
意味着 不能用空格、换行符这些东西？
Is it a strcpy of how it's getting passed around, which means...
是通过 strcpy 传递的吗 意味着……
strcpy will keep copying up to a null byte
strcpy 遇到空字节 会停止拷贝
which is going to be a pain for you.
这会给你带来麻烦
So yeah, this is definitely something to remember here.
所以 这个一定要记住
So then where are we going?
那接下来我们做什么
Yeah.
对
So...
所以……
Okay, so then what we're looking for is something like a win function.
我们找的是类似win函数的东西
That's our next intuition here.
这是我们的下一个想法
So the way I would look
我通常这么看
there's a nice handy dandy sub view.
有个很方便的子视图
I almost always run strings on the binaries.
我基本上都会用strings命令，过一下二进制文件
So it'd be hard here
所以这里会有点难
because there's like 15 different levels in here
因为这里有 15 个不同的级别
but strings would at least tell us all the strings
但strings命令能显示所有字符串
so we can look for like flag.
我们就能找到"flag"
Well, we actually need the next level's password.
这里我们需要的，其实是下一级的密码
Yeah, we want level two password.
对 我们要第二级的密码（口误，实际是第三关）
we do
确实需要
Where?
在哪？
Oh, perfect. Okay.
哦 太好了
Level two password.
第二关的密码
Where is it? Okay, yeah, great.
在哪？ 好的 太棒了
So I don't...
我不会...
I'm like terrible at IDA.
我对 IDA 一窍不通
so this is very weird to... People think that I'm actually good at this.
就很奇怪，人们竟然都认为我擅长IDA
Okay.
好的
So level two password
所以 第2关密码
we found out where it prints it.
我们找到了打印它的位置
Awesome.
太棒了
We double click that.
我们双击它
That takes us to
这会带我们进入...
now we're in the pseudocode view.
现在我们在伪代码视图
We're in read-only data.
我们在查看只读数据
So this is data that's in the binary at this address.
这些数据在二进制文件的这个地址
I didn't do checksec on it
我没有对它执行checksec
but I assume that this is gonna be non-PIE.
但我觉得这应该是非 PIE 的
So these will be at fixed locations.
所以这些数据在固定地址
And then level two password.
然后是第二关密码
So then I'm gonna hit the X button to do, Cross references.
然后我按 X 键进行交叉引用
So this shows you what other parts of the code
这会显示代码的其他部分
that this is analyzed that reference this specific thing.
哪些地方引用了这个特定内容
You have to be very careful.
你得注意
This is not the ground truth.
这并非完全准确
This only does like a direct reference.
这只能显示直接引用
So when the code like says, hey, load that address there.
当代码说 加载那个地址时，才会显示出来
But if it's part of like an array
但如果它是数组的一部分
if you X ref like the third or fourth array element
如果你查看第三或第四个数组元素的交叉引用
but it only accesses it over an iterator
但只通过迭代器访问它
it will not like the decompiler can't know that it actually accesses it.
反编译器不知道代码实际上访问了它
So this is only like direct access.
所以IDA只记录直接访问
So you do have to remember that.
所以你得记住这点
Okay.
好的
So now I double clicked on that.
现在我双击了它
That takes us now to the IDA view of where we are in here.
这带我们进入了 IDA 视图 显示我们当前的位置
And then I'm going to hit tab to decompile it.
然后我按 Tab 键来反编译
We want the level three password.
我们要的是第三关密码
All right.
好的
Okay.
Well, we have level one password, level two.
我们已经有了第一级和第二级的密码
So I hit slash.
我按了 /
To then search, you can see the slash at the bottom.
来搜索 你可以看到底部的斜杠
And I'm going to type in level.
我输入“级别”
what if I really remind by telling you could do ctrl F
也可以按ctrl+f
That was going to be my next one.
这是我的下一步
I think slash, though, does like incremental search, just like in less.
我觉得 / 可以进行增量搜索 就像在 less 里一样
Yeah, there we go.
好
Okay.
好的
Level.
级别
We want the level.
我们需要关卡
Wait, what is this Level 2 not synchronize?
等等 这个关卡2不同步是什么？
Level three password.
关卡3密码
There we go, boom.
成了 搞定
So we do have our target.
目标找到了
Okay, great.
好的 太好了
So we have our target is level three password.
目标是level3password
Oh no, I don't have it set up.
哦不 我还没有设置好
Usually,
通常
well, I guess I go
嗯 我得
I go back and forth on if I have the addresses on here
我会反复检查这里是否有地址
but you can see the address is here.
不过你能看到地址在这儿
It's 401178.
是 401178
So we want to overwrite.
所以我们需要覆盖它
And, okay, so we have our target here.
好的 目标就在这里
Okay, this is where I should start.
好的 从这里开始
Okay, this is where I'm just going to take notes here.
好的 这里开始我得做笔记了
Let's do 401178.
我们输入 401178
Okay.
好的
40, well, we already know the password
40 哦，已经看到密码了
but this is cheating.
但这样是作弊
Don't look at the password.
不要看密码
um okay four zero one one seven eight
嗯 好的 401178
and now we need to go back
现在我们需要回去
so i'm going to hit
我要点
this is the other thing i really don't like about ida is like
我对 IDA 的另一个不满是
the ida view and the pseudocode view the backs are different
ida视图和伪代码视图的返回功能不同
and so what i mentally wanted to do was to go back
我想要回到
to that original decompilation view that we were looking at
之前看的那个原始的反编译视图
of the level two of the stack overflow function um
第二关的stack_overflow函数的反编译
but If I kept pressing back here I don't know that I would get to that
但如果一直在这儿后退，我不知道能不能回到那里
because it's a different backwards and forwards thing.
因为这俩像在不同的前进后退序列中
This is why your brain gets melted by the tools that you use.
这就是为什么 越用这个工具，大脑越乱
Like nobody should think about that.
谁都不应该考虑这些
You should just be able to go back and forward just like a web browser.
你应该像在网页浏览器里一样，前进后退
Anyways, okay.
好了 算了
Nope, that was the wrong one.
不对 这个错了
That will let us down.
那样会让我们失望
Stack overflow.
栈溢出
Great, okay.
好的 没问题
And we want, so we're in verify user.
我们在verify_user中
So now let's look at the binary code.
现在看看二进制代码
So, okay, the way this is working is
所以 是这样的
So 30
if I remember correctly
如果我没记错的话
when it does var underscore 30
在 var_30 中
this means 30 hex.
这个 30 是十六进制的
Is that right?
对吗？
So store pair 29 and 30 at the stack pointer
所以 将 X29 和 X30 存储到SP指向的栈地址中
first decrement
先减小SP
or for increment the stack.
或增加SP
That doesn't make sense.
这听起来不对
Should be decrement, right?
应该是减小 对吧？
So it should be minus 30.
所以_30应该是-30
I actually find IDA very poor.
我觉得 IDA 很不好用
Like I actually like objdump, but yes.
我实际更喜欢 objdump
Okay, so minus 30 hex is...
好的 -0x30是
I think if you double click this
如果你双击这个
it will show you,
它会显示出来
oh yeah, var 30.
哦 对 var_30
Yeah, so this is minus
对 这是减号
this actually does mean minus right on the left.
左边这个确实是减号
This is the view of the stack layout.
这是栈布局的视图
When you double click on a variable in the disassembly view
当你在反汇编视图中双击变量时
takes you to this.
会带你到这里
And then if I escape
然后按 Esc 键
does bring me back here.
会带我回来
So, okay, so decrement the stack pointer by 30 hex.
所以 把栈指针减去 0x30
and then copy at that location 29 and 30, 30 there
然后在这里保存一下x29和x30
set this all up, and then,
设置好后
yeah, load pair,
LDP
again, exactly the same thing, stack pointer plus 30 minus 30.
栈指针加 30 减 30
Okay, so we should be able to...
好的 我们应该能……
Okay, I wanna do this in a very silly way.
好的 我打算用一种非常蠢的办法来做
I want to do like a whole PwnTools thing.
我想完全用 PwnTools 实现
You guys will be okay if I just do really crappy code, right?
如果我只写一些烂代码 大家没问题吧？
The difference is if you choose to do it.
区别在于你们是否愿意去做
Okay.
好的
Oh no, there's going to be a pain because of the bytes, isn't it?
哦不 字节问题会很麻烦 对吧？
God, I hate Python.
天啊 我最烦 Python 了
Why do people do this?
大家为啥要这么做？
fine
好吧
okay where where i refuse
好吧 但我拒绝
okay
好的
行
echo b
显示 b
no e
不对，e
okay we want
我们希望溢出的
so our buffer is
目标缓冲区是
if we look at this
如果我们看一下这个
our buffer is on v3 and v...
我们的缓冲区在 v3
Okay, so this is the first strcpy is admin.
好的 第一个 strcpy 拷贝的是 admin
We want the second.
我们需要第二个
Wait, where's the other strcpy?
等等 另一个 strcpy 呢？
Oh, is this an...
哦 这是个...
It's an inline strcpy
这是个内联的 strcpy
because it's a constant value.
因为它是一个常量
Okay, don't want to reverse that.
好的 我们可不想逆向它
Oh, you can see the admin and then the n
哦 你可以看到 admin 里的 n
it has to get the N in there.
得把 n 放进去
That's what this one is.
就是这个
Yeah, because it's doing four bytes.
是的 因为它一次处理四个字节
It's doing the A-D-M-I-N and then the N.
它在处理 A-D-M-I 再加上 N
Okay, so strcpy the first argument is the destination, right?
好的 strcpy 的第一个参数是目标 对吧？
Stack pointer.
栈指针
Okay, I hate this.
好吧 我真讨厌这个
Okay.
好的
So stack.
栈
So this is eight.
这有 8 个
Let's do...
我们来试试...
How many A's do we all think we need?
大家觉得需要多少个 A？
20个？
28个？
Yeah.
嗯
So I like to do that plus B.
我喜欢这样做 加上 B
So I just like to I don't know.
我喜欢
You can use, I'm sure you all are very good using cyclic call
你们可以用 我相信你们都很擅长用cyclic
and doing all that to find out that stuff.  I don't know.
来弄清楚需要几个字节来覆盖缓冲区
That's all new things and stuff.
这些都是新事物
For me, I like a good old fashioned, just print out the stuff.
我个人更喜欢传统的方法 直接把东西打印出来
Bus error.
总线错误
Okay, great.
好的 太棒了
We can GDB.
我们可以用 GDB 来调试
Again, I can do this because this is an ARM system.
同样 我能这么做是因为这是个 ARM 系统
You will not have that funny, that...
此时这个funny没啥用
That use.
那种用法
Incorrect.
错了
These are A's, not B's.
这些是 A 不是 B
Yeah.
对
Hire good people.
招好人
It's probably the point where we should debug this.
估计得调试一下
Just randomly trying stuff in front of people is good.
当着大家的面随机试试也挺好
I think it's 8
我觉得是8
Oh, duh, because there's two 8-byte buffers.
哦 对了 有两个 8 字节的缓冲区
So it wasn't eight, it was 16.
所以不是 8 是 16
Okay.
行
Yep, okay, so great.
好的 太棒了
Now we got there
我们现在到了
and now we, let's see
现在我们来看看
where do we want to go?
我们想去哪儿？
We want to go slash X. I put it here, 78, 11, 40.
我们要去 \x78, \x11, \x40
I shouldn't probably have to change the 40. I'm just going to do this.
我应该不需要改 40， 这样就行
Look at that.
看看这个
And why are we looping forever?
我们为什么一直在循环？
Exactly.
对
So let's do
那我们来
what's 8 plus C.
8加4是多少？ C 。
Oh, I did that.Can you believe that?  I did.
哦 我成功了 你敢信？我做到了
Hex plus four.
十六进制的加四
All right.
好的
So look at that.
看 就是这个
We did that.
我们做到了
You guys all did it.
你们都做到了
You can do it on the homework.
你们在作业中也能做到
It'll open in 50 minutes.
50 分钟后会开放
So good luck.
祝你们好运